<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The doctrine of particular unconditionate election (before time) asserted and prov'd by God's word against the Quakers, papists, and Arminians : in answer to a challenge given the author (by the Quakers) to make good (by the Scriptures of truth) the abovesaid doctrine ... / by Ja. Barry.</title>
            <author>Barry, James, fl. 1650-1702.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 153 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 64 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A69684</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B969A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R27208</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09713635</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09713635</idno>
            <idno type="VID">44024</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A69684)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 44024)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1348:27)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The doctrine of particular unconditionate election (before time) asserted and prov'd by God's word against the Quakers, papists, and Arminians : in answer to a challenge given the author (by the Quakers) to make good (by the Scriptures of truth) the abovesaid doctrine ... / by Ja. Barry.</title>
                  <author>Barry, James, fl. 1650-1702.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 115 [i.e. 117] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Election (Theology)</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:44024:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:44024:1"/>
            <p>THE Doctrine of Particular Unconditionate ELECTION (Before Time.)</p>
            <p>Aſſerted and Prov'd by God's Word, againſt the <hi>Quakers, Papiſts,</hi> and <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In Anſwer to a Challenge given the Author, (by the <hi>Quakers</hi>) to make good (by the Scriptures of Truth) the aboveſaid Doctrine.</p>
            <p>Wherein is evidently diſcovered,
<list>
                  <item>I. That the aboveſaid Doctrine, rightly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood and believ'd, (with Application to ones ſelf) is the great Enemy of Sin, both in the Heart and Life of a true Believer; and that which keeps the Believer from Deſpair in the deepeſt Deſertion and Temptation.</item>
                  <item>II. That the Doctrine of Free-will and General Redemption, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is an Inlet to, and an Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rager of Sin; and which leads (in the end) to horrid Deſpair, under powerful Awakenings in the natural Conſcience of an Unregenerate Man.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>For there ſhall ariſe falſe Chriſts and falſe Prophets, and ſhall ſhew great Signs and Wonders; inſomuch, that (if it were poſſible) they ſhould deceive the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Elect,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Mat. 24.24.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Wherefore the rather, Brethren, give all diligence, to make your Calling and Election ſure, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 Pet. 1.10.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>By <hi>Ja. Barry,</hi> an unworthy Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author, 1700.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:44024:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:44024:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Impartial READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Am to inform thee, that in the time of the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, when <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Quakeriſm</hi> ſmil'd ſo (ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cably) on each other, (as the two Religions (if I might ſo call them) which are neareſt of Kin of all the Religions (viſibly) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs'd in theſe Kingdoms) the People called <hi>Quakers</hi> ſent me a
<pb facs="tcp:44024:3"/>Thraſonical Challenge in Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, (which was afterwards pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed in Print) to prove (from the Scriptures of Truth) the Four Doctrines here following. <hi>(1.) The Doctrine of the Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of this fleſhly Body, which Dies and turns to Duft. (2.) The Doctrine of Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, by the alone Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of Jeſus Chriſt, freely imputed. (3.) The Doctrine of Imperfection (in Sanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) in the moſt Mortified Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever, while in this World. (4.) The Doctrine of Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Unconditionate Election before Time.</hi> All which the <hi>Quakers</hi> do ſtiffly (and peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torily) deny, as by their Printed Book (againſt me) doth evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:44024:3"/>appear. Their Challenge I was reſolv'd to anſwer in Print, to let the World ſee what Hetero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox and Heretical Principles that deluded (and ſeduced) People, do hold and teach for true Religion. Beſides my Reſolution (herein,) I oblig'd my ſelf by promiſe, to my Congregation, that I would (in the Strength of Chriſt) prick the Bladder of their Blaſphemous Pride, by proving (and making good) by the Scriptures of Truth, the aboveſaid Doctrines. For my Encouragement (wherein,) my Congregation did (unanimouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) ſtand by me, reſolving I ſhould be at no other Charge (here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>about) but the Studying part. Paper was Bought, the Printer agreed with; and juſt as the
<pb facs="tcp:44024:4"/>Preſs was ready to begin, the Storm came ſo ſuddenly on the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in <hi>Dublin,</hi> that we were ſoon ſcattered aſunder. The Providence of God calling on us, to ſecure our Lives, inſtead of Printing Books. The reaſon why I have been ſo long ſilent in this Cauſe, is, the want of that help I had from my Flock in <hi>Dublin.</hi> If any generous noble Spirited Chriſtians (who love Chriſt's Cauſe better than they do the Mammon of this World) will ſtep in to my Encouragement, in ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying the room of my abſent Friends, they ſhall (in a very ſhort time) ſee the Four Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines above-mention'd clear'd up and made good from God's Word, (Maugre all the Jeſuiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal
<pb facs="tcp:44024:4"/>Craft and Subtilty, whereof that People ſeem to be Maſters) The reaſon why I have ſingled out the laſt of the four Doctrines, rather than any of the other three, to diſcover and confute the <hi>Quakers</hi> pernicious Hetero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxy (in the foundation Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of true Chriſtianity) is two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> becauſe that in denying and oppoſing the Doctrine of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, unconditionate Election (before time) they do manifeſtly Rob God of his Soveraignty and Praiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> becauſe of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural tendency, which the denial of this Doctrine of a particular, unconditionate Election (before time) and the holding and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagating
<pb facs="tcp:44024:5"/>its contrary, <hi>(viz.)</hi> The Doctrine of Free Will to good (in every Man) of Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Redemption, and a Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary, Conditional Election, with falling from Grace; hath to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage Men in Living a licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, looſe Life; and to neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate Mens final deſpair of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when the Naural Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence (in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nregenerate Men) comes to be under powerful A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakenings, for Sin committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Law of God.</p>
            <p>That I do the <hi>Quakers</hi> no wrong, in charging them with Robbing God and encouraging Men to Live in Sin; as alſo their laying a Foundation for Mens deſpair of ever being ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in their way of Conditional
<pb facs="tcp:44024:5"/>and Temporary Election, will evidently appear to him who reads and compares with Gods revealed Will, what is diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this ſmall Tract: And in caſe any noble Spirited Chriſtians will but encourage the Work (as already hinted) I do not ſo much as doubt, but that the Spirit of God will enable me to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate (from Gods own Word) that the <hi>Quakers</hi> in denying the Reſurrection of the Body, and the Juſtification of a Sinner, by the alone Righteouſneſs of the Son of God, (freely imputed) without any regard had to any Qualifications inhering in the Perſon of the Sinner Juſtified, do deny all ſound and ſaving Religion; And as touching their
<pb facs="tcp:44024:6"/>Sinleſs Perfection, (attainable in this Life) whereof they make ſuch Brags; it ſhall be made plain, that (herein) they both belye the Spirit of God, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict the experience of all ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Believers, both in Heaven and Earth.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:44024:6"/>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of Election before Time.</head>
               <p>GOD did before all Time, by his unchangeable Counſel, moſt freely, unchangeably, and from all Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, elect and chooſe unto himſelf (out of Lapſed <hi>Adam</hi>'s fallen Poſterity) a certain number of Perſons, (which can neither be leſſened nor encreaſed) to partake of his ſpecial ſaving Grace to Salvation, by Jeſus Chriſt his Son, to the Praiſe of the Glory of his own Grace.</p>
               <p>What I have now aſſerted (for truth,) if God enables me to demonſtrate and make good by Scripture, as (I doubt not) he will, then will it unavoidably follow, (all the Wit and Malice of Men and Devils cannot overthrow it,) that God hath paſſed by, and Reprobated o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
               <p>In the Propoſition now laid down, there are three things to be conſidered, in order to a clearing up, and making good the Point in Diſpute. <hi>Firſt,</hi> The
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:44024:7"/>Act of God, and the Objects thereof, which are both held forth and intended in the Scriptures following, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.4. <hi>According as he hath choſen us in him. Jo.</hi> 15.19. <hi>I have choſen you,</hi> &amp;c. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.13. <hi>God hath choſen you,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>In the Scriptures now quoted, we have God Electing or Chooſing, and then the Objects of his Election or Choice, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Particular Perſons, on whom that Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of God fixeth, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Some parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Perſons.</p>
               <p>That God's Act of Election hath fixt on ſome particular Perſons, not on all in general, as the Enemies of Election would fain have it, the following Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments will evince.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 1. If God hath made a Promiſe of Life and Salvation to ſome particular Perſons only, then hath he elected and choſen to himſelf a certain number of Perſons, to whom alone (excluding all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) that Promiſe of Grace and Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall be made good.</p>
               <p>But God hath made a Promiſe of Life and Salvation to ſome particular Perſons only, (excluding all others;) therefore God hath elected and choſen to himſelf a certain number of Perſons, to whom (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:44024:7"/>all others) the Promiſe of Life and Salvation ſhall be made good.</p>
               <p>That God hath made a Promiſe of Life and Salvation to ſome particular Perſons only, (excluding all others) is evident and plain to ſuch as acknowledge the Scriptures of the <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> to be of Divine Authority. <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.7. <hi>And I will eſtabliſh my Covenant between me and thee, and thy Seed after thee, in their Generations, for an everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Covenant, to be a God to thee, and to thy Seed after thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here the Judicious and Unprejudic'd reader may plainly ſee, that <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed were particular Perſons, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from all other Nations and People, which were round about him: And theſe it pleaſed God of his meer Soveraign Grace, to ſingle out for his own peculiar Uſe, that they may be a Holy People, to bear his Name, and to give him a pure and ſpiritual Worſhip and Service, which ſhould be according to his own Holy Inſtitution and Divine Appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: And that they may be made Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the promiſed Inheritance, which was the ſure Poſſeſſion of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven, of which the promiſed Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> was but a Type and Shadow.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:44024:8"/>
               <p> The People of the <hi>Jews</hi> was but a ſmall People when God fixt his Love on them, and called them. <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.6, 7, 8. <hi>For thou art an holy people unto the Lord thy God, the Lord thy God hath choſen thee to be a ſpecial people unto himſelf, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all people that are upon the face of the earth. The Lord did not ſet his love upon you, nor chooſe you becauſe ye were more in number than any people, for ye were the feweſt of all people, but becauſe the Lord loved you: And becauſe he would keep the Oath which he had ſworn unto your fathers, hath the Lord brought you out with a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty hand, and Redeemed you out of the ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> of Bondmen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame Promiſe which was made to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed under the <hi>Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament</hi> Diſpenſation, is confirmed by the <hi>New.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And evident it is, that as God choſe and called <hi>Abraham</hi> under that dark Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation, with whom he entred into a Covenant of Grace; the Benefit of which was to be of equal extent to himſelf and his Children, even ſo many of them as were the Children of the Premiſe. So under the Goſpel Diſpenſation God (who is a free Agent, acting all he doth in a way of Soveraignty) ſaw fit to make known, by the Goſpel, that among the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:44024:8"/>
                  <hi>Gentiles</hi> alſo he had a ſelect and choſen People, on whom he had decreed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr the Riches of his free Grace, through the plenteous Redemption that is in his Son Jeſus Chriſt; and that purſuant to his own immutable Decree and Purpoſe, electing and chooſing them before Time began. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.39. for the Promiſe is to you and to your Children, and to all that are afar off, even as many as the Lord our God ſhall call.</p>
               <p>Here is that Promiſe formerly menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, which looks at <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Children, and alſo diſcovers the graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Deſign of God, to make a certain number of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> actual Partakers of the ſelf-ſame Grace and Bleſſing.</p>
               <p>The manner of the Apoſtle's expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing himſelf, is full of Clearneſs and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuity, proving, that the promiſe of that Grace and Salvation is not deſigned for all and ſingular the <hi>Gentile</hi> Sinners that then were, or in after times ſhould be in the Word, but he limits and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrains the Promiſe to a certain peculiar number, leaſt Sinners ſhould miſtake the Apoſtle, and conclude, that becauſe he had laid down an univerſal Term, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, And to all that are afar off, he (by way of Explanation) ſhews what the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit means by that univerſal Term, adding
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:44024:9"/>even as many as the Lord our God ſhall call, in which he plainly ſhews, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincibly proves, that none of the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile</hi> Sinners ſhall ever partake of God's ſpecial Grace, but ſuch as are (in time) effectually called out of a State of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to a State of Juſtification and Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication; the which is never granted to any, but in the Right of a Covenant-pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, which Covenant-promiſe reſpects that gracious Act of God, electing and chooſing in Chriſt his Son, as many of <hi>Adam</hi>'s Poſterity, both of <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi> as his own Soveraignty pleaſed, according to that of the Apoſtle: <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.30. <hi>Moreover, whom he did praedeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, them he alſo called, and whom he called, them he alſo juſtified, and whom he juſtified, them he alſo glorified.</hi> And our Saviour himſelf, in <hi>Jo.</hi> 10.16. deſigns the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> whom God had in his ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting Love, given in charge to him, in thoſe Expreſſions: <hi>And other ſheep I have, which are not of this fold, them alſo I muſt bring; and they ſhall hear my voice,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 2. If among the many thouſands of People, who hear the Goſpel Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but ſome (and that very few compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratively) are ſavingly Converted, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:44024:9"/>Mercy, are Juſtified and Sanctified, and are made to Perſevere in a courſe of Faith and Holy Life; then God hath ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and choſen only a certain peculiar number of Men to Life and Salvation.</p>
               <p>But among the many thouſands of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who hear the Goſpel Preached, but ſome only are ſavingly Converted, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Mercy, are Juſtified, are Sanctified, and do finally Perſevere in a courſe of Faith and Holy Life.</p>
               <p>Therefore God hath elected and cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen only a certain peculiar number of Men to Life and Salvation.</p>
               <p>There is nothing more evident than that the greateſt number, even of thoſe People, who are outwardly called by the Goſpel, do ſlight and contemn the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, and the Grace offered therein: Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that of our Saviour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.16. <hi>For many are called, but few are choſen. Luke</hi> 14.16, 17, 18, 19. That Parable of the King, who made a great Supper, to which the King (by his Servants) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited the Gueſts, notwithſtanding which many of them made blind Excuſes, and ſhifted it off. By which Practiſe in the Gueſts we are to underſtand, that great ſlight and contempt which worldly mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Sinners put on the Lord Jeſus and his great Salvation, (wrought for the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:44024:10"/>Elect) which God offers in the Goſpel, the which they undervalue, preferring the Accommodations of this periſhing World, before that great and precious Salvation.</p>
               <p>To this alſo pertinent is that of <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 10.16. <hi>But they have not all obeyed the Goſpel, for</hi> Eſaias <hi>ſaith, Lord who hath believed our report?</hi> Rom. 9.27. Eſaias <hi>alſo crieth concerning</hi> Iſrael, <hi>Though the number of the children of</hi> Iſrael <hi>be as the ſand of the ſea, a remnant only ſhall be ſaved.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now then, if among thoſe many, who are Externally called, and the very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, who make a Profeſſion, there are but very few who ſavingly Believe, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and finally Perſevere in a courſe of Faith and Holy Life; then it is beyond all Controverſy, that thoſe few who ſo Believe, Repent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are particular Perſons, whom free Grace elected to that ſtate of Believing and Perſevering; and the reſt, who were (by far) the greater number, were left to inward Blindneſs and hardneſs of Heart, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.7. <hi>What then?</hi> Iſrael <hi>hath not obtained that which he ſeeketh for, but the election hath obtained it, and the reſt were blinded: According as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, God hath given them the ſpirit of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:44024:10"/>ſlumber; eyes, that they ſhould not ſee; and ears, that they ſhould not hear, unto this day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arg.</hi> 3. If God hath choſen Perſons by Name, to be Partakers of Life and Salvation by Chriſt his Son, then hath he choſen particular Perſons.</p>
               <p>But God hath choſen Perſons by Name, to be Partakers of Life and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation by Chriſt his Son.</p>
               <p>Therefore God hath choſen particular Perſons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The major Propoſition is not queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned; the Minor or Aſſumption is ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the expreſs Teſtimony of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. Rev. 13.8. <hi>And all that dwell upon the earth, ſhall worſhip the beaſt, whoſe names are not written in the Lamb's book of life.</hi> Luke 10.20. <hi>Notwithſtanding, in this rejoyce not, that the ſpirits are ſubject unto you, but rather rejoyce becauſe your names are written in Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Philip. 4.3. <hi>And I intreat thee alſo true yoke fellow, help thoſe women which laboured with me in the Goſpel, with</hi> Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>alſo, and with other my fellow-labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, whoſe names are in the book of Life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Argu.</hi> 4. If <hi>Jeremiah</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> &amp;c. were particular Perſons Choſen and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:44024:11"/>Lov'd of God before they were Born, then God did Elect and Chooſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Perſons to Life and Salvation; but <hi>Jeremiah</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> &amp;c. were par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Perſons, Choſen and Lov'd of God before they were Born.</p>
               <p>Therefore God did Elect and Chooſe particular Perſons to Life and Salvation.</p>
               <p>That <hi>Jeremiah</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> &amp;c. were particular Perſons, no Man of Senſe will deny; that they were Beloved of God before the natural Birth, the word of God is full and expreſs. <hi>Jer.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.11.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Argu.</hi> 5. If God knows his Elect from all others, before he calls them in Converſion, then hath God Elected particular Perſons to Life and Salvation.</p>
               <p>But God knows his Elect from all others, before he calls them in Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
               <p>Therefore God hath Elected and Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen particular Perſons to Life and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
               <p>That Gods Praecognition (or fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge joyned with his purpoſe of Grace to Save his Elect) goes before his actually calling them in effectual Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, is beyond Diſpute. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.29, 30. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19. <hi>Jo.</hi> 13.18.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:44024:11"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Argu.</hi> 6. If they who believe in Time, were, before their Believing, ordained to Eternal Life, then did God Elect and Chooſe particular Perſons unto Life and Salvation.</p>
               <p>But they who believe in time, were, before their Believing, ordained to E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Life.</p>
               <p>Therefore God hath Elected and Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen particular Perſons unto Life and Salvation.</p>
               <p>That Gods Praeordination of Perſons to Life and Salvation, doth preceed (or go before) Believing and Repentance; is plain from <hi>Acts</hi> 13.48. <hi>And as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as were ordained to Eternal Life Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved.</hi> Rom. 11. <hi>The Election hath obtained it.</hi> Jo. 10.26. <hi>But ye Believe not, becauſe ye are not of my Sheep, as I ſaid unto you.</hi> From which Scriptures it is moſt plain, that none do, or can (in time) Believe and reput to Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but ſuch Perſons as are theretofore appointed by Gods gracious purpoſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Argu.</hi> 7. If the Term Elect doth ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie and preſuppoſe a Calling or Choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſome particular Perſons or Things, out from among other Perſons or Things, then hath God out of ſo many, Elected ſome particular Perſons unto Eternal Salvation.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:44024:12"/>
               <p> But the Term Elect doth ſignifie and preſuppoſe a Calling or Chooſing ſome particular Perſons or Things out from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong other Perſons or Things.</p>
               <p>Therefore, God hath out of many, Called and Choſen ſome particular Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons unto Eternal Life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Argu.</hi> 8. If the Lord Jeſus did lay down his Life but for a certain particular number of Sinners, then did God Elect and Chooſe a particular number to Life and Salvation.</p>
               <p>But the Lord Jeſus did lay down his Life for a certain particular number of Sinners.</p>
               <p>Therefore God did Elect and Chooſe a particular number to Life and Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>That the Lord Jeſus did lay down his Life for a certain particular number, is obvious and plain to him that can but Read. <hi>Jo.</hi> 10.15. <hi>As the Father know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth me, even ſo know I the Father; and I lay down my Life for the Sheep.</hi> With this accords that of <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Titus.</hi> Chap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.14. who gave himſelf for us, that he might redeem us from all Iniquity, and purchaſe to himſelf a peculiar People, Zealous of good Works. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.25. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> love your Wives, even as Chriſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:44024:12"/>alſo Loved the Church, and gave himſelf for it,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The Sheep of whom Chriſt ſpeaks, can be underſtood to be no other but Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, even ſuch as Dy'd in the Faith be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Incarnation, with the Believers of that preſent day, and all who in time to come were to Believe in him: And theſe are the Souls who were by the Father committed to the Paſtoral care and charge of Chriſt the Great Shepherd of the Sheep, as Sheep are committed to the care and charge of an under Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd.</p>
               <p>For theſe Chriſt lays down his Life: To theſe, he (by his Spirit) actually applys the virtue of his Death: Over theſe he Watches: And to theſe only, (excluding all others) he gives Eternal Life.</p>
               <p>That theſe were given to Chriſt by the Father, to be redeemed and brought to Glory, appears from <hi>Jo.</hi> 6.39.</p>
               <p>And this is the Fathers Will which hath ſent me, That of all which he hath given me, I ſhould looſe nothing, but ſhould raiſe it up at the Laſt Day. <hi>Jo.</hi> 17.6. <hi>Thine they were, and thou ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt them me,</hi> &amp;c. And Verſe 2. <hi>As thou haſt given him Power over all Fleſh, that he ſhould give Eternal Life to as
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:44024:13"/>many as thou haſt given him.</hi> ☞ <hi>Mark this Reader? To as many as thou haſt given him.</hi> This plainly proves that God did commit to the care and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of Chriſt his Shepherd, a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain particular number to be Juſtified and Saved by him; and therefore not all the Race of fallen Mankind, as <hi>Papiſts, Arminians, Quakers, Free-Willers,</hi> &amp;c. vainly teach and hold.</p>
               <p>Another Conſideration, which is full of clearneſs, to convince and ſatisfie any right in their Minds, That not <hi>Adams</hi> Poſterity in General, (as the <hi>Hereticks</hi> above named would fain have it) but a certain particular and definite number were Elected and Choſen by God, and by him given to Chriſt his Son, to be Redeemed and Saved; is Chriſt his refuſing to concern himſelf for any others, in the diſcharge of his Office of Interceſſor, as appears from <hi>Jo.</hi> 17.9. <hi>I Pray for them, (that is, for the Elect, for whom he had undertaken as Vedem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>y and Surety) I Pray not for the World, (that is, thoſe of the World, who were by God left in a Reprobate State and Condition)</hi> as is evident from <hi>Jo.</hi> 17.14. <hi>I have given them thy Word, and the World hath hated them becauſe they are not of the World; even as I am not of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:44024:13"/>the World.</hi> Here are two diſtinct Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tys deſcribed by Chriſt, the one is Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for, the other is not; the one is ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the other hates; the very Practice of the latter denotes the Perſons to be Children of another Father, diſtinct from thoſe they hate. There is nothing more diſcovers Men to be the Children of the Devil, than their hating Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and not loving thoſe who appear to be Godly. 1 <hi>Jo.</hi> 3.10. <hi>In this the Children of God are manifeſt, and the Children of the Devil; whoſoever doeth not Righteouſneſs is not of God, neither he that loveth not his Brother.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As Love to God, his Truth, and ſuch as bear his Image, is an infallible Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of an Elect Child of God. <hi>Jo.</hi> 13.35. 1 <hi>Jo.</hi> 3.14. 1 <hi>Jo.</hi> 4.7.</p>
               <p>So to hate God, his Truth, and ſuch as bear his Holy Image, is the indelible Character of a Reprobate deſigned for Eternal Deſtruction. 1 <hi>Jo.</hi> 3.10.</p>
               <p>The ſecond thing in the Propoſition to be conſidered, is the End and Deſign of God in that Act of his in Electing and Chooſing, which is twofold. Firſt, as it reſpects the Creatures Elected, <hi>viz.</hi> that they might partake of the Special Grace of God here on Earth, and of Eternal Glory in the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:44024:14"/>through Chriſt his Son, according to that of <hi>Paul, Epheſ.</hi> 1.4. <hi>According as he hath Choſen us in him before the Foundation of the World, that we ſhould be Holy and without blame before him in Love.</hi> 2 Theſ. 2.13. <hi>Becauſe God hath from the beginning Choſen you to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, through Sanctification of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and Belief of the Truth. Verſ.</hi> 14. <hi>Whereunto he called you by our Goſpel, to the obtaining of the Glory of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> 1 Theſ. 5.9. <hi>For God hath not appointed us to Wrath, but to obtain Salvation by our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, with reſpect to God, Elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Glory of his Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign, Free, and rich Grace, might be Extolled and Praiſed for ever, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as the Apoſtle expreſſeth it in <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.6. <hi>To the Praiſe of the Glory of his Grace, wherein he hath made us accepted in the Beloved. Verſ.</hi> 11, 12. <hi>In whom alſo we have obtained an Inheritance, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing predeſtinate, according to the purpoſe of him who worketh all things according to the Counſel of his own Will; that we ſhould be to the Praiſe of his Glory, who firſt truſted in Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third thing in the Propoſition to be conſidered, is to take Notice of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:44024:14"/>the Properties in that Act of God Electing.</p>
               <p>Thoſe Properties are in number three. Firſt, God in Electing and Chooſing ſome Sinners to himſelf out of the corrupted Maſs of fallen Mankind, on whom he purpoſed to ſhew Mercy: He did Elect and Chooſe them moſt freely; there was nothing at all in the Objects Elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and Choſen, that could move God wherefore he ſhould Elect one Sinner more (or ſooner) than another; for as fallen into Sin, and equally obnoxious to the Curſe of the Law and the Wrath to come, were all the Sons and Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Adam,</hi> lookt on by God, when he fixed his Electing Love on ſome, and actually rejected and paſſed others by, on whom the moſt High God, (as an uncontrolable Soveraign) purpoſed to execute the fierceneſs of his Wrath for Sin. The reaſon or impulſive cauſe of this Difference, which the tremendous God ſaw fit to make between Sinners, equally guilty and obnoxious to the Curſe and Wrath of God, is not to be ſought out of God himſelf. An Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample and lively Inſtance hereof we have in <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.11. which the Wiſe God hath ſeen ſit ſhould be recorded, on purpoſe to ſtop the mouth of Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:44024:15"/>reaſon, which is ſo wretchedly prone to Queſtion (and Diſpute againſt his Soveraignty over his Creatures. <hi>The Children being not yet Born, neither ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving done any good or evil, that the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of God, according to Election, might ſtand, not of Works, but of him that cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth. It was ſaid unto her, the Elder ſhall ſerve the Younger. As it is Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten.</hi> Jacob <hi>have I Loved, but</hi> Eſau <hi>have I Hated.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Wiſe God foreſeeing the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blind Reaſonings and Cavillings of Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Mens unſanctified Brains, againſt the Doctrine of Gods abſolute Soveraignty, in diſpoſing of the Eternal concerns of his rational Creatures, fallen by Sin into a ſtate and condition of Miſery, through their own default; hath ſeen good (for the vindication of his own Prerogative) to make known to the Sons of Men, (and that by the unerring Wiſdom and unqueſtionable Authority of ſo great a Man as <hi>Paul,</hi> the great Apoſtle of the <hi>Gentiles</hi>) the reaſon of Gods Method in proceeding to Elect ſome of fallen Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, to a ſtate of Life and Salvation through a Redeemer, and Reprobating others, leaving them for ever to periſh in that Sin and Miſery, into which they did (without any conſtraint) wilfully
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:44024:15"/>plunge themſelves, to be no other than his own moſt free and holy Will, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he alone is the undoubted So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign of the World, who hath an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſputable right to determine what to do with, (or how to diſpoſe of) Sinning Rebels, without being (any way liable to the controulment of any of his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, eſpecially ſuch of them as (by Sin) have forfeited their very Being to the Divine Juſtice; and who (while in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reconciled State) are not capable of knowing him, or of being ſubject to his Divine Law.</p>
               <p>The good Will and Pleaſure then of the Bleſſed God, is the Source and Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain whence the great Diſparity between the Elect and the Reprobate World doth ſpring, not any thing in the Creatures themſelves, as <hi>Arminian</hi> Cavillers dream and conceit it doth: This will evidently appear, if the Reader will but (with a becoming modeſty and unprejudic'd judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) read the whole Chapter at length, and (with fervent Prayer to God for the Wiſdom of his Spirit) look narrowly into, and with ſobriety conſider the 11th. and the 16th. Verſes, where it plainly appears, that the two conceited Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications, of which the Enemies of Elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion are uſually proud, and which they
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:44024:16"/>hold and teach, are the procuring cauſe of the Difference between the good and the evil Men on Earth, <hi>viz.</hi> the Free Will in Man, and the good Works which un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate Men, do but conceit they do; they are both met with, and equally diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carded by God, from having any room or place among the cauſes which put God either upon Chooſing the Elect or reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Reprobate. Mark the 11th. Verſ. <hi>That the purpoſe of God according to Elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion might ſtand, not of Works, but of him that calleth.</hi> With this agrees <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2 8.9. <hi>For by Grace are ye Saved through Faith, and that not of your ſelves; it is the Gift of God. Not of Works, leaſt any Man ſhould boaſt.</hi> And Tit. 3.5. <hi>Not by Works of Righteouſneſs which we have done, but according to his Mercy he hath Saved us,</hi> &amp;c. Vain unregenerate Man would fain perſwade himſelf that he is worſe than Threadbare Rags of his polluted Morality; negative and poſitive is a covering ſufficient not only to hide his Ulcerous and plague Sores of Guilt and Vileneſs, from the pure and All-ſeeing Eyes of an Infinite Majeſty, but alſo to deck and adorn his Soul, ſo as to beſpeak him an Object ſit for a Holy God to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold with delight: Oh horrid deluſion! worſe than Frenzy, or Madneſs it ſelf; this
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:44024:16"/>being but a Temporary Malady, which may (by the uſe of ordinary means) be holpen, but that the Bane and Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Immortal Soul, which nothing but the deſpiſed Grace of God in Chriſt can cure; ſuch miſerably deluded Souls will not find it eaſy to believe, that to think ſo highly of their own Qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, is the greateſt bar or hinderance which keeps them from Salvation. Read alſo (with care) Verſ. 16, <hi>So then, it is not of him that Willeth, nor of him that runneth; but of God that ſheweth Mercy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let the Adverſaries of the Doctrine I am now vindicating, but conſider that Man as fallen into Sin and Miſery of his own accord, is the Object of Election and Reprobation; and let them (if they can) tell or ſhew me how a Natural Man in his Lapſed, Guilty State, can (poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly) either Will or Act any thing, but what is (both for matter and manner) moſt vile and abominable in the ſight of that God, who is Purity and Holineſs it ſelf in the Abſtract.</p>
               <p>And if ſo, wherefore then ſhould the moſt Juſt and Holy God be conceived to elect Men for that which he can do no other than hate and loath, as the beſt Duties of an unregenerate Perſon, are both contrary to the Nature of God,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:44024:17"/>and alſo repugnant to his Juſt and Holy Law?</p>
               <p>When unregenerate Men talk and brag of their Duties and Qualifications, as that which muſt recommend them to God, and purchaſe for them a Right to the Crown that fades not away they, think, and ſpeak as Men in a midnight Dream, not underſtanding what they ſay, or whereof they affirm; and the head Spring of this their Boaſting of their Qualifications, is the profound Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance and Luciferian Pride, which ſways their unrenewed Spirits, having never paſſed under the killing Severity of the Law of God, ſet home on the Conſcience by the Spirit of Bondage, to prepare them for healing by the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Until this Work of the Lord paſs on the Soul, no Child of <hi>Adam</hi> can (poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly) prize the Son of God, or ſee him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be utterly undone, till (with the Rich Man in the Parable) the unquench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Flames of Hell diſcover his Miſery to him, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.23. From what hath been obſerved from the Scriptures now referred to, plain it is, that God, in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting ſome and Reprobating others of <hi>Adam</hi>'s Poſterity, cannot (without Blaſphemy) be ſaid to elect or chooſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:44024:17"/>Man to a ſtate of Life and Glory, for any thing of good, which he foreſaw, would be in the Sinner, fallen into a ſtate of Sin and Miſery: And therefore, if there was nothing of foreſeen Good in the Creature elected, for which God had reſpect to him more than to another, it muſt unavoidably follow, that in God electing, (not in the Sinner elected) is the impulſive or moving Cauſe, <hi>(viz.)</hi> His own Soveraign good Pleaſure.</p>
               <p>God (as hath been already obſerved) in Electing and Reprobating Men, looks on them as fallen; and guilty Creatures, who had wrought their own Miſery, by their voluntary breach of his Royal Law. To none of them was the moſt High (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny way) obliged. He might have ſent them all to the ſame Place and Condition of the fallen Angels, whoſe Conduct and Example they followed, in rebelling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Holy Soveraign. And which of all the Reprobates (now in Hell) will it avail, to diſpoſe the Point of God's Soveraignty with him? or to enquire why or wherefore he hath left them in that ſad and deplorable Eſtate of Sin and Miſery? Pertinent to the Buſineſs in hand, is that Query which <hi>Auguſtin</hi> puts in his Book of the City of God; <hi>Quis fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit Reprobum?</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Who made the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:44024:18"/>Reprobate?</hi> to which he himſelf replies, <hi>Quis niſi Deus? Who</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>but God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again he Queries, <hi>Quare Deus fecit Reprobrum? Why did God make the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate?</hi> to which he anſwers, <hi>Quia ita voluit: Becauſe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>it was his Will.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again he Queries, <hi>Quare Deus voluit Reprobum facere? Why</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>was it God's Will to make the Reprobate a Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate?</hi> He anſwers the Cavilling Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt (or Saucy and Pragmatical Enquirer) with that of <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 9.20. <hi>O Homo tu quis es, Qui Reſpondeas Deo? O Man, who art thou that Replyeſt againſt God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If <hi>Auguſtin</hi> were now living on Earth, and ſhould Read the Reply which <hi>Grevincovius</hi> (that Blaſpheming Proud <hi>Arminian</hi>) made to the Query which <hi>Paul</hi> put to the called <hi>Corinthian,</hi> who excelled in the Gifts of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.7. <hi>For who maketh thee to differ? and what haſt thou, that thou haſt not received?</hi> to which <hi>Grevincovius</hi> moſt Arrogantly and Blaſphemouſly replies, <hi>I my ſelf make my ſelf to differ.</hi> I ſay, if <hi>Auguſtin</hi> were to Read this <hi>Arminian</hi>'s Anſwer to <hi>Paul,</hi> it would not be difficult to gueſs at what rate <hi>Auguſtin</hi> would treat his Inſolency.</p>
               <p>If the abuſed Grace of God changed him not before Death, it is moſt dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:44024:18"/>to think, and ſeriouſly to conſider, how little the Freewil and Learning, of which he was greatly proud, do now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail him at the Barr of the Great Judge; no doubt but he finds (in woful Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence) what an <hi>Impar Congreſſus</hi> (or une<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual Match) he is, for the great <hi>Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah</hi> to diſpute Matters with. Oh! that Men of his Spirit and pernicious Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were Wiſe, to conſider things aright before they ſee and feel their Folly in the unquenchable Flames of God's Wrath in Hell.</p>
               <p>Let it be farther conſidered, how ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the Spirit of God is in charging on <hi>Adam</hi> and all his Off-ſpring (without Exception) the breach of his Law, and (on that very account) accounting them all guilty Criminals, and unclean Pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Sinners, who (by their voluntary A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtacy) have forfeited his Favour and loſt his Bleſſed Image, wherein the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Happineſs of the Rational Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture conſiſted, as the Apoſtle witneſſeth <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.23. <hi>For all have ſinned, and come ſhort of the Glory of God.</hi> And in <hi>ver.</hi> 19. <hi>Now we know, that what things ſoever the Law ſaith, it ſaith to them, who are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law, that every mouth may be ſtopped, and all the world may become guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty before God.</hi> The concluſion whereof
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:44024:19"/>he ſets down in <hi>ver.</hi> 20. <hi>Therefore by the deeds of the law there ſhall no fleſh be juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in his ſight, for by the law is the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of ſin:</hi> With <hi>Paul</hi> concurrs all the Prophets, and the other Pen-men of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures, ſetting forth the wretched Condition of all Mankind by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy of <hi>Adam,</hi> the natural and faederal Head of his Children.</p>
               <p>The Condition then of all <hi>Adam</hi>'s Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity being ſuch, as renders every Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner Culpable before God, and not only ſo, but utterly uncapable of willing or acting the leaſt part of that Duty, which God's Law requires to a helping or reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering himſelf out of that his Miſery. It is moſt plain and obvious to every en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened Underſtanding, that by the Tenure of the firſt <hi>Adam</hi>'s Covenant, all are Born Heirs of the Curſe and Wrath of an offended God; and are (by reaſon of that Spiritual Impotency, which is inflicted on <hi>Adam</hi>'s Nature as a Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for breaking God's Law) as (alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether) unable to believe in an Atoning Saviour, (when offered by God in the Goſpel of his Grace) as they are to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the Condition of that Holy Law of God, the Violation and Breach whereof hath Caſt and Condemn'd (at God's Barr) the whole Race of Mankind.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:44024:19"/>
               <p> Man's wretchedneſs and Miſery then is of himſelf, he can truly and juſtly blame none for it but himſelf. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.29. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13.9.</p>
               <p>This granted, it (unavoidably and by neceſſary conſequence) follows, that God is moſt Juſt and Righteous in Sealing (to the day of his Wrath) with the black Character of Reprobation, that part of <hi>Adam</hi>'s Poſterity, on whom he hath (fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly) reſolved to Glorify, that adorea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and tremendous Attribute of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſtice, for breaking his Juſt and Righteous Law.</p>
               <p>And where is the Man, who will under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to prove God Unjuſt and Unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, in caſe he had dealt with the Elect themſelves, as he hath done with the Reprobates, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Seal them up to the Judgment of the Great Day of his Wrath? God is Debtor to none of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi>'s Children, unleſs to Damn and Forſake them for ever, for their (Devil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like) Apoſtacy and Rebellion.</p>
               <p>In this adoreable and tremendous Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation of his, in Reprobating the greateſt part of Mankind, and electing to himſelf (out of the failen and corrupted Maſs) ſome few of Mankind, on whom he purpoſed to Glorify the Riches of his Grace, through Chriſt his Son. He acts
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:44024:20"/>towards both, in a way of abſolute Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty, ſo that as the Reprobates can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſay they have not merited that Curſe and Miſery, which is like to be their Portion for ever, ſo neither ſhall the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect be ever able to attribute their Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation to any other Cauſe, beſides the Soveraign free and rich Grace of God, which (had it pleaſed God) might have ſixt its hold on the Reprobates, making them the Elect, while they themſelves were overlookt and paſſed by.</p>
               <p>For my own part, I muſt (ingeniouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) confeſs, that I am ſo far from refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting on God, as (any way) Unjuſt or Partial, for dealing with <hi>Adam</hi>'s Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren as he doth, that I am rather aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd to think, that any of <hi>Adam</hi>'s Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate Off-ſpring ſhould ever eſcape that Curſe and Wrath, to which they were all equally Born Heirs apparent. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.3. <hi>And were by nature the children of wrath, even as others.</hi> This, this was the State and Condition of the Elect themſelves, as they are the natural Off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring of <hi>Adam:</hi> But the Banner of God's free Grace, and undeſerved Love and Pitty hath been (by the Arm of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Soveraignty) effectually diſplayed over them, when in their Blood and Wretchedneſs, even then when God
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:44024:20"/>firſt laid the Foundation of their Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in Election. According to <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.4, 5, 6, 7. and <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. to the 10. <hi>ver. Well may every juſtified believer cry out with</hi> Paul, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.33. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Oh the depth of the Riches, both of the wiſdom and knowledge of God! how unſearchable are his Judgments, and his ways paſt finding out!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this bottomleſs Profundity (or Depth) of God's Unſearchableneſs, the Wit and corrupt Reaſon of Unregenerate Men, with all their acquired Parts, are ſwallowed up and confounded; by reaſon whereof it comes to paſs, that many times ſuch as are admired for their great Reaſon and Learning, will not allow the Creator of the World that Priviledge, which they readily grant to a Man like themſelves, <hi>(viz.)</hi> To decree or act any thing but what their blind Reaſon and perverted Judgment can ſee a Reaſon for it. Oh what an Age do we live in! wherein the Immenſity and Unſearcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs of God is (on every occaſion of Mens diſputing Principles of Religion) called on to hold up the Hand at the Barr of thoſe Mens Carnal Reaſon, who indeed have loſt the uſe of right Reaſon.</p>
               <p>Of ſuch Men I would gladly know, whether they can, (with all their Mother
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:44024:21"/>Wit, deckt and adorn'd with all their Academical Learning,) Fathom the depth of the Created Ocean, or tell the exact number of the Stars, and what In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence they have on Humane Bodies? If they can tell how the Soul and Body of man are United? Or how the Bones grow in the Womb of the Woman with Child? With many other Secrets in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, not only difficult, but even Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to be found out by the Wit and Learning of <hi>Adam</hi>'s Children: Witneſs the many Learned Philoſophers, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the World abounded, whoſe Wit and Learning came vaſtly ſhort in find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out and tracing the Almighty in his Works of Creation and Providence: From whence I Argue, <hi>A Minore ad Majus,</hi> From the Leſſer to the Greater. If all the Mother Wit and acquired Parts and Learning of the Children of <hi>Adam</hi> could never find out many Secrets in the Works of Creation and Providence, how much more impoſſible is it for them, to find out the Almighty Creator himſelf to perfection?</p>
               <p>The Query which <hi>Zophar</hi> the <hi>Naa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mathite</hi> put to <hi>Job,</hi> will never be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered by any Creatures in Earth or Heaven any other way than in the Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, <hi>Job</hi> 11.7. <hi>Canſt thou by ſearching
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:44024:21"/>find out God? canſt thou find out the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty to perfection?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And from what Source or Fountain Mens Atheiſtical and Sawcy Reflections on God, (for making ſuch a difference between <hi>Adam</hi>'s Children, in Saving but few (in Compariſon) and Damning the reſt) ſhould ſpring, I cannot tell, unleſs from their profound Ignorance of the Immenſe and Incomprehenſible Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of God's Being, and their not owning and believing his abſolute Soveraignty over his Creatures.</p>
               <p>I Appeal to the Conſcience of every Savingly Englihtened Man, who Reads this, whether this wilful and affected Ignorance of God, and their denying his abſolute Soveraignty over his Creatures, be not the very Portal or Door, at which the horrid Profaneneſs and matchleſs Debaucheries of this worſt of Ages (which now lays the Kingdoms open to utter Ruine) have entred the Stage.</p>
               <p>This is that which the Devil and his buſy Agents (the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Jeſuits) aim'd at, when (in the late K. <hi>J.</hi> his Reign) they obtained the King's Royal Prohibition, forbidding Miniſters, both <hi>Non.</hi> and <hi>Con.</hi> to meddle (in Preaching) with the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Election and Reprobation. They well knew how Subſervient the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:44024:22"/>keeping the People Ignorant of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Election, would be to open the Floodgates to Profaneneſs and Debau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery, and (conſequently) prepare <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> for a ready Reception of curſed and damning Popery.</p>
               <p>The denying the Doctrine of God's Soveraignty, in Electing and Reproba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Lapſed and Guilty Rebels, and teaching and maintaining, both in Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit and Print, Freewill to good in Unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate Men, as alſo the Doctrine of general Redemption is a Doctrine which is altogether Unſcriptural; and becauſe of Mens Violence and Peremptorineſs in Teaching and Propagating the ſame, and their Obſtinacy in refuſing to receive and ſubmit to the contrary Doctrine, which is according to the Scriptures and the only Doctrine, which deſigns the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of Sin in the Hearts and Lives of true Believers; and the Promoter of true Holineſs: God moſt Juſtly puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſuch People with a giving them up, not only to believe the moſt Nonſenſical Lyes, (for true Religion) but even to wallow like Swine in the Mire of the groſſeſt Immoralities, even to an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the very Pagan World.</p>
               <p>To illuſtrate the point I am now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending againſt the <hi>Quakers</hi> and <hi>Armini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:44024:22"/>viz.</hi> That God in Electing ſome and Reprobating others, doth Act therein moſt freely, as an abſolute Soveraign: Let them give me leave to put this Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion to their Reaſon and Conſcience, (ſuch as it is) ſuppoſe that all the ſeveral Parties in the City, who differ in their Mode (or Way) of Worſhipping God, ſhould (in their reſpective Meetings, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of Worſhipping God) lay all their Heads, Hearts and Hands together, to contrive and carry on a Plot againſt the King and the Fundamental Laws of the Kingdom, with a full intent to deſtroy both the one and the other; to which Plot all the ſeveral Parties do (as one Man) harmoniouſly and unanimouſly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, the Law condemns not only the Practice (as Traiterous and Treaſonable) but Sentences the very Perſons (all and ſingular) who are prov'd to have had any hand in ſuch a Plot, to a ſhameful and cruel Death.</p>
               <p>The Plot comes to be Diſcovered, upon Diſcovery, the King, who hath the Executive Power of the Law in his own hand, he conſiders the matter, and find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that all theſe ſeveral Parties, (whom he took to be Loyal Subjects) are turned Rebels; as moſt evidently appears by the unnatural Plot, lately engaged in by
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:44024:23"/>them all, againſt both his Perſon and Government; for which, both he and they know full well the Law condemns them all alike.</p>
               <p>The King, to whom the Executive Power of the Law belongs, according to his Prerogative, he Nominates two Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect Parties out of all the reſt, <hi>viz. Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> and <hi>Arminians,</hi> to whom he reſolves to extend his Favour, in giving to them his Royal Pardon; the other ſeveral Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties (diſtinct from them) he reſolves to leave them to the Sentence of the Law, to undergo the deſerved Penalty thereof, for that horrid and unnatural Rebellion. I would fain know what the <hi>Quakers</hi> and <hi>Arminians</hi> could object againſt the King of <hi>England,</hi> for paſſing an Act of Indem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity (or Free Pardon) on the People cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Quakers</hi> and <hi>Arminians,</hi> and leaving all the other Parties to ſuffer Death.</p>
               <p>Seeing that (herein) the King Acts by Prerogative, not according to Deſert; for the <hi>Quakers</hi> and <hi>Arminians</hi> deſerved Death as well as the reſt, who are exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded out of the Pardon: My reaſon tells me that the <hi>Quakers</hi> and <hi>Arminians</hi> would be ſo far from charging the King with Injuſtice or Partiality, that they would rather ſound forth his Praiſe, for ſaying them by his Favour and Mercy,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:44024:23"/>(no way deſerved) whom in ſtrictneſs of Juſtice, he might have left to the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of the Law.</p>
               <p>And in caſe any of the Criminals con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to Die, ſhould offer to murmur againſt the King, for making ſuch a Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between his (equally) guilty Subjects, would not the <hi>Quaker</hi> and the <hi>Arminian</hi> both Plead the Kings Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive for ſaving themſelves, when at the ſame time, and by the ſame Soveraignty he paſt by the reſt; and ſhall the King of Kings be Diſputed againſt and Reflected on for Acting (in matters of the like nature) by his own undoubted Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative.</p>
               <p>If any ſhould be ſo ſaucy and bold, as to demand a reaſon why or wherefore the King of <hi>England</hi> ſhould leave ſeven or eight ſeveral Parties out of his Royal Pardon, and extend the Benefit thereof only to two Select Parties, who were both as liable to Death (by the Law) as the others; the Anſwer is ready, it is the Kings Soveraign Will and Pleaſure to make the two Select Parties Nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in his Pardon, Objects of his Pity and Mercy, and the reſt to be the Objects of his incenſed Juſtice, to undergo that Death and Miſery which they (by Rebei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion) brought upon themſelves.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:44024:24"/>
               <p> Now in all this, hath not the Potter power over the Clay of the ſame lump, to make one Veſſel to Honour, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to Diſhonour? <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.21.</p>
               <p>Reader, I pray conſider, that the lump in the place now quoted, intends no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than Men and Women, whom God (the abſolute Soveraign of the World) Decreed to Create: The making Veſſels is Gods Creating Mankind with a purpoſe to permit their Fall.</p>
               <p>His making one Veſſel to Honour, and the other to Diſhonour, is Gods Creating one with a ſixed purpoſe to recover him out of that fallen State, into which he was to fall, (and that by Soveraign Grace) the other he leaves to Die and Periſh in that wretched State, into which he (of his own default) fell.</p>
               <p>In this Procedure God is altogether free; neither can the Creature ſo left by God, any way reflect on God, as dealing unjuſtly or unequally with him; and the reaſon is, becauſe God is under no Tye or Obligation to give Grace to that Creature, who (of his own accord) did abuſe and throw away that ſtock of Grace, whereby he was rendred capable of keeping the Law of his Maker; and who by the Inſtinct of his vitiated and corrupted Nature, doth obſtinately op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:44024:24"/>and reſiſt the means of Cure, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded and tendred in the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>So that the point in Controverſy, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween me and the Adverſaries already Named, is in this compariſon propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Verſe laſt quoted, lively ſet forth; from which it is apparent, that the deſign of the Apoſtle is to prove that God (as the undoubted Soveraign of the World) who Acts what him pleaſeth, and that according to the Counſel of his own moſt Holy Will, decreed to make ſome of the corrupted Maſs to be Veſſels of Mercy, and of the reſt Veſſels of Wrath; and that by Electing ſome unto himſelf, upon whom he purpoſed to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow his Love, with all the means tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to fit and prepare thoſe Perſons ſo Elected and Choſen, for the actual en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of that Love.</p>
               <p>Such as a Redeemer, to Die for them; Faith, whereby they ſhould be made Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of that Redeemer, with all the ſaving Graces of the Spirit, promiſed in the Covenant of Grace, with final per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeverance in Grace to the end; the reſt (as hath been before obſerved) he left (or paſſed over) purpoſing to leave them in that wretched and deplorable Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, into which they (cauſeleſly) plung'd themſelves.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:44024:25"/>
               <p> Neither is God therefore the cauſe why the Reprobate is Sinful and Wicked, but his own Will; which being left to its own natural freedom, did moſt freely and readily chooſe that which was by Gods Law forbidden, upon pain of Gods Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure and Curſe.</p>
               <p>The ſecond Property in Gods Act of Election, is its unchangeableneſs, and therefore, moſt certain it is, that he or ſhe whom God hath once purpoſed to Love and Save, ſhall never finally (or to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally) fall away from Grace, or miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry eternally, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.11. <hi>The Counſel of the Lord ſtandeth for ever, the Thoughts of his Heart to all Generations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What is Gods Election of ſome to Life Eternal, (and the means leading thereto) but the Birth or Product of his own Counſel? <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.11. <hi>The purpoſe of God according to Election, muſt ſtand.</hi> And Oh: what an unſpeakable cauſe of rejoycing is this very Conſideration to that Man, or Woman; who find in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the Fruits (or Effects) of the New Birth, to think and believe, that they (in particular) are choſen to Life Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, by him who cannot change that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of his, wherewith he hath purpoſed to Save ſo poor and miſerable a Sinner,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:44024:25"/>as the effectually called Sinner looks on himſelf to be.</p>
               <p>Neither is the poor weak Believer to doubt, but that thoſe Sins and Backſlide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, both of his Heart and Life, for which he will be but too apt to fear and conclude, God will at length caſt him off, were all perfectly known to God, even then when he Elected him to Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; notwithſtanding which, God fixt his Love and embraced the poor Sinner in the Boſom of his irreverſible Decree, when nothing of Lovelineſs, (but rather the contrary) appeared to the Eye of Gods Praecognition (or fore knowledge) in the Soul, ſo pitcht on by his Decree.</p>
               <p>Whom God once loves with that E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting Love, he loves them to the end. <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.8. <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Jo.</hi> 13.1. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.29. And as Gods Act in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting is without change, ſo (in the third place) it was from Eternity; though the work of effectual Calling and Saving Converſion be in time, yet Gods decree and purpoſe of beſtowing that Grace and Mercy on the Elect Sinner was before time: So witneſſeth the Apoſtle, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.18. <hi>Known unto God are all his Works, from the beginning of the World.</hi> Epheſ. 1.4. <hi>According as he hath choſen us in him before the Foundation of the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:44024:26"/>World.</hi> 2 Theſ 2.13. <hi>From the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning hath God choſen you.</hi> Rev. 17.8. <hi>Whoſe Names were not written in the Book of Life, from the Foundation of the World.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Electing Love of God it is from one Eternity to another, as it did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mence before time; ſo when time ſhall be ſwallowed up of endleſs Eternity, this Love of God (to his Elect, and choſen in Chriſt) will be (and continue) the ſame for ever.</p>
               <p>And therefore, let that Believer, who feels himſelf inwardly and frequently annoyed with thoſe diſcouraging Fits of fickleneſs and unconſtancy, in walking with God (in the way of New Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence) take Sanctuary here by Faith, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying to himſelf the ſweet Benefits of theſe Properties of Gods Electing Love, filling both his Head and Heart with the thoughts and fixed perſwaſion, that the Bleſſed God, who is the Infinite Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign of the World, (who Acts all things which pleaſeth himſelf, according to the Counſel of his own Will) hath of his own good pleaſure choſen him a poor, unworthy, empty, nothing Creature, to be a Veſſel of Mercy, (through Jeſus Chriſt) to the Praiſe of the Glory of his own Grace: And that Love, wherewith God hath Loved him, it began towards
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:44024:26"/>him before he had an actual Being, yea, before the World was: And as that Love of God was ſet on him before time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan, ſo when time it ſelf ſhall be no more, that Love of God to him ſhall ſtill be endleſs, like God himſelf. Nothing more conduceth (under God) to Heart Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in the ways of God, then to be well Verſt in Underſtanding and Believe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, (with application to ones felſ) theſe Fundamental Principles of Goſpel Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
               <p>And this one thing I deſire the Reader to remember, and carefully to obſerve, <hi>viz.</hi> That if there were no other Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to evince and make good the Truth I have now aſſerted, than the Arduous and Elaborate endeavours of Satan and his buſy Agents, both in Preaching and Printing againſt the Doctrine of Election and Reprobation, it were ſufficient. The Devil and the Pope know full well how deſtructive and pernicious to both their Kingdoms, the bringing Sinners to the Scriptural Knowledge and right Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving this Doctrine will be.</p>
               <p>And therefore for preventing hereof, the Doctrine it ſelf muſt be expos'd in the blackeſt hue, as a Doctrine which makes Men proud, ſecure, and careleſs of good Works, and which leads Men to looſe
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:44024:27"/>Living; and in the end to final Deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: And as the Doctrine it ſelf is ſhot at by the <hi>Romiſh</hi> and <hi>Arminian</hi> Archers, ſo the moſt zealous and bold Aſſertors and Maintainers of it, are ſet out in the moſt odious and black colours, which Envy and Malice it ſelf can deviſe; but maugre all the Craſt and Envy of Devil and his moſt ſubtil and induſtrious Tools the Doctrine of particular Election (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore time) is plainly held forth and aſſerted in the Writings of <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Prophets; and the Holy Apoſtles: And in caſe Divine Providence calls to a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering Condition for defence of it, I do not doubt but God hath a Sealed number in theſe Kingdoms, (known to himſelf) who will be enabled to Seal the Truth of it with their deareſt Blood.</p>
               <p>An Objection or two lyes in the way to be anſwered, before I can proceed to what remains behind.</p>
               <p>Object. 1. <hi>The Doctrine of particular Election puffs Men with Pride.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The contrary to this the Devil himſelf knows to be true.</p>
               <p>For I doubt not but Satan hath made his Obſervations, that none of all Gods
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:44024:27"/>called Children, have more abounded with Humility and ſelf Abaſement, than thoſe who have had the higheſt aſſurance of Gods Electing Love: None but theſe can rightly admire and adore the Grace and Love of God in Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To me, who am leſs than the leaſt of all Saints, is this Grace given,</hi> &amp;c. crys that great Apoſtle of the <hi>Gentiles, Epheſ.</hi> 3.8. <hi>This is a faithful ſaying, and worthy of all acceptation, That Jeſus Chriſt came into the World to ſave Sinners, of whom I am the chief.</hi> 1 Tim. 1.15. <hi>For I am the leaſt of the Apoſtles, that am not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be called an Apoſtle, becauſe I Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted the Church of God.</hi> 1 Cor. 15.9. <hi>But by the Grace of God I am what I am. Verſ.</hi> 10. It is to be obſerved, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all the Apoſtles, none was more highly advanced, (in reſpect of extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Manifeſtations and Goſpel Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, than <hi>Paul</hi> was; and yet among all the Apoſtles none more abaſed: No greater admirer of Free Grace than he was; and indeed, not only <hi>Paul,</hi> but others alſo, both under the <hi>Old Teſtament</hi> and under the <hi>New,</hi> whom Free Grace ſingled out to be Veſſels of Mercy: Theſe were ſtill addicted to go out of themſelves in a way of ſelf Abaſement, and crying up the Riches of Gods Grace and Mercy
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:44024:28"/>every way free and undeſerved by them. And herein I appeal (moſt freely) to the Perſonal Experience of every regenerate Believer, (now Living) whether they do not find in themſelves, that the nearer they come to know and perceive the Love of God to themſelves in particular, the more vile they are in their own eſteem; and the more the Sight and Senſe of their own Nothingneſs grows and abounds, the more are they inwardly ſtirred up to Adore and Magnifie the Riches of Gods Free Grace, who hath vouchſafed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard ſuch poor contemptible Worms, as they judge themſelves to be.</p>
               <p>Object. 2. <hi>The Doctrine of particular Election cuts off the force and ſtrength of all Threatenings and Warnings which are Recorded in the Scriptures, as a Curb and Bit, to reſtrain Men from Sin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The ever Bleſſed and Holy God, who decreed to elect and chooſe a particular number to Salvation, hath decreed alſo the means of bringing them to that End, whereof thoſe Threatenings and Warnings ſcattered here and there in God's Word, are a part; the which the good Spirit of God makes (effectual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) uſeful to work and encreaſe in the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:44024:28"/>Elect, (called to State of Grace) the Filial and Reverential fear of God; as alſo to Caution them againſt all kind of Decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings in the way of Holy walking with God, in the way of new Obedience to his Holy Commandments; the which God hath revealed in his Word, to be the only way, in which true Believers muſt go to an actual Poſſeſſing the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed Inheritance, according to <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.1, 2, 3. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.1, 2, 3. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.14.</p>
               <p>Theſe Divine Threats and Warnings are (through the ſaving Influence of the Spirit of Grace) made a powerful Bit and Curb, to reſtrain the ſavingly Converted from returning (with Approbation and Delight) to former (and forſaken) Folly, and not only ſo, but to keep them more cloſe to their Duty in a Goſpel Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance on Chriſt, their Mediatorial Head, for all manner of Supplies, till they come to Glory.</p>
               <p>Thoſe Threats and Warnings (if they were ten thouſand times more than they are) will never curb or reſtrain any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate from loving and liking Sin.</p>
               <p>'Tis true, that (through the common Operation of the Spirit of God) ſuch Threats and Warnings may for a time in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence a Hypocrite to a keeping him from the External groſs Act of Sin, and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:44024:29"/>a putting him on doing many things which are (Morally) good in themſelves. But Alaſs! what will this avail, while the State of the Man is unchanged, and his Heart unrenewed. Sad Inſtances hereof are Recorded in God's Word; witneſs <hi>Pharaoh, Exod.</hi> 7.4. and <hi>Judas Mat.</hi> 26.15. <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.5. with many other Reprobates, whoſe Names are left on Record in the Book of God, who were neither reſtrained from Sin, nor yet kept back from running headlong to Hell, with this Bit in their Mouths. The Spirit of God (by the Holy Prophet) gives a full Deſcription of the natural Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of wicked Hypocrits, as touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Incorrigibleneſs of their Hearts, in going on in Sin, not only under God's Rod, but alſo under his favourable Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation, which (one would think) ſhould win them to Repentance, <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.3. <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.9, 10, 11. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 26.10, 11. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4, 5.</p>
               <p>Object. 3. <hi>If I be elected to Life eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal (before time,) I may live as I liſt; I need neither to Believe, to Repent, or to uſe the means of obtaining Salvation. And though I live after the Fleſh, I ſhall be Saved, being elected.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:44024:29"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To this threadbare Objection (which is commonly in the Mouths of all Cavillers againſt the Doctrine of Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) I anſwer in two Particulars.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> This Objection doth not (in the leaſt) find any Encouragement from the Doctrine of particular Election (before time,) as will evidently appear by the Inſeparableneſs of the End, and the means aſſerted and held forth in the Word of God, and conſtantly maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Orthodox againſt <hi>Papiſts, Arminians,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>He who hath elected to Life eternal, he hath alſo elected to the means; ſuch as, believing in the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, held forth and offered in the Goſpel; Repenting for Sinning againſt God; advancing in Holineſs, and Perſevering in the ſame to the end: From whence it plainly appears, that he who makes this Objection, is either wilfully ignorant not (in the leaſt) underſtanding the Doctrine of Election, (according to Divine Revelation) or which is (unſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kably) worſe, an affected Caviller and a wicked Subverter of the Goſpel. Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe I ſhould Query of the <hi>Papiſt,</hi> the <hi>Arminian,</hi> the <hi>Quaker,</hi> and <hi>Freewiller,</hi> (who are all agreed in oppoſing and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crying
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:44024:30"/>the Doctrine of particular Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on before time, and Perſeverance to the end, whether they believe that God hath decreed, or abſolutely determined in himſelf) how long he (or they) ſhall Live or continue in this World? The Anſwer will (undoubtedly) be in the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmative, <hi>(viz.)</hi> That God hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed (or determined) in himſelf, how long he (or they) are to live or continue in this World.</p>
               <p>If then (ſay I) you believe, that God hath decreed (in himſelf) how long you are to live or continue in this World, what need you to mind any of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns of this World, for the Support of Humane Life? why will you ſo Inſatia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly covet the periſhing Riches, and the tranſitory Pleaſures of the preſent World, ſeeing God hath decreed how long you are to live?</p>
               <p>The Anſwer again will be, he that hath decreed how long I am to live in this World, he hath alſo decreed and (in his revealed Will) commanded me to Exerciſe my Reaſon, and my other na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Faculties, in order to precure and make uſe of the ordinary means, ſuch as Food, Ravment, Phyſick, and the like, whereby (in an ordinary way) the Life and Health of the Body are ſecured and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:44024:30"/>maintained. Here (in the Concerns of the Body) they are ſharp and witty e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, even to an out-doing thouſands of the Children of God. But in the Concerns of the Soul they are as Corrupt and Heterodox, as they are ſound and rational in the other.</p>
               <p>If a <hi>Papiſt</hi> or an <hi>Arminian</hi> ſhould fix his Purpoſe of Building a Houſe in ſuch or ſuch a place, it cannot be (rationally) ſuppoſed, that he intends to Build with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Materials; therefore my Reaſon tells me, that in order to accompliſh that his Purpoſe, he hath alſo purpoſed to provide all the ſeveral Materials ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for ſuch a Purpoſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qui ſeriò vult finem, Media etiam ad finem illum tendentia vult:</hi> He who (in good earneſt) wills the end, he alſo wills the means leading to that end, is a ſure Rule, both in Logick and Divinity. And why theſe Popiſh <hi>Arminian</hi> Cavillers ſhould not allow it its proper place in the Doctrine of Election (before time,) I can underſtand no other Reaſon for it, than either becauſe God hath Judicially ſmitten them with blindneſs of Mind, that they ſhould not be able to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand or believe this amazing Doctrine of Election before time, or elſe becauſe God hath left them (as he did <hi>Pharaoh</hi>)
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:44024:31"/>to harden themſelves, that they might, with the greater Acuteneſs and Stubborn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, oppoſe and withſtand his Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty, in Electing ſome and Reproba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting others of the ſame fallen and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted Maſs, and that before time.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> As there can be no Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment more Cogent and Irrefragable, to evince and prove a Man to be either a Fool or a Madman, than his reſolving to expect the Accompliſhment of the end, (ſuch as Building a Houſe or Living in the World) without the uſe of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionate means leading to ſuch ends; for there is no Argument which more ſtongly proves a Man or Woman to be of the number of Reprobates, than to expect or hope to go to Heaven, in the continued and approved Neglect of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving in the Son of God, Repenting of Sin, living a Holy Life, and Perſevering in the ſame to the end of Life.</p>
               <p>Object. 4. <hi>The Doctrine of Election before time, doth not only encourage to Sin, but it leads People to final Deſparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for preventing of which, all imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable care ought to be taken, to ſuppreſs and decry it.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:44024:31"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To this Horrid and Blaſphemous Objection I ſhall (in Chriſts ſtrength) Anſwer in four Particulars.</p>
               <p>And Firſt, I do boldly affirm in the Name of the ever Bleſſed Trinity, That this Blaſphemous Objection did (origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally) ſpring from that Spirit which char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the Son of God with caſting out De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils by <hi>Beelzebub,</hi> which (if I miſtake not) is the unpardonable Sin againſt the Holy Ghoſt, and ſuch as peremptorily (with allowance and approbation) perſiſt in making and liking the ſame, againſt the Doctrine of Election, ſo plainly revealed and ſo poſitively aſſerted by the Holy Ghoſt; I am not afraid to declare and pronounce them the Children and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors of thoſe <hi>Phariſees</hi> (now in Hell) who vented that unpardonable Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my againſt the Holy Ghoſt. <hi>Mat.</hi> 12, 24.32. Let all Cavilling Adverſaries who bring this Objection againſt the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Gods abſolute and free Election (before time) have a care they be not found Ranked among thoſe mighty Sinners, who in the height of their Wickedneſs, run themſelves moſt deſperately upon the thick Boſſes of the Almighties Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler. <hi>Job</hi> 15.26.</p>
               <p>Secondly, If the Doctrine of Election be ſuch a dangerous Doctrine as leads to
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:44024:32"/>Licentiouſneſs, and which (in the end) brings Men to Deſparation. I would fain know how it comes to paſs that the Enemies of this Doctrine are ſuch Slaves to their Brutiſh Luſts, and why ſo many of them Die in Deſpair, when under powerful Awakenings and common Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victions in their guilty Conſciences?</p>
               <p>Thirdly, I do with greateſt confidence and certain aſſurance (grounded on the Word of God, and backt with my own Perſonal experience) affirm, That as the right Knowledge and Believing of the Doctrine of Election (before time) with a particular application thereof to ones ſelf, is the only Doctrine that ſets the Heart of a true Believer againſt all Sin, and which ſecures and keeps the Believer from Deſparation in the time of the deepeſt Deſertion, and moſt violent Temptation; ſo the Doctrine of Free Will and general Redemption is a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which encourageth to Sin, and which neceſſarily leads to Deſparation.</p>
               <p>Here two things are to be demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Firſt, That the Doctrine of Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (before time) rightly underſtood, and particularly applied by Faith, is the only Doctrine which engages the Heart of a ſound Believer againſt all known Sin, and which fortifys and ſecures the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:44024:32"/>Believer againſt Deſparation in the time of the deepeſt Deſertion, and the moſt violent Temptation.</p>
               <p>Secondly, That the Doctrine of Free Will and general Redemption, is a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which encourageth to Sin, and which (neceſſarily) leads to Deſparation.</p>
               <p>The firſt of theſe will evidently appear to him that rightly conſiders and believes the Particulars following.</p>
               <p>Firſt, the Purpoſe and Deſign of God the Father (in Electing) which was, That his Elect and Choſen, who were fallen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Sin and Miſery in <hi>Adam,</hi> their Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and Faederal Head, might be deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and (by ſtrong hand) reſcued out of that ſtate of Sin and Miſery, and made effectual Partakers of that Liberty and Redemption, purchaſed by Chriſt his Son, the Sponſor and Surety of his Elect.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the deſign of Chriſt (the Surety and Sponſor of the Elect) in the whole Work of Mediation, which he undertook to go through for the Elect (which his Father had choſen in him) which was to purchaſe for, and (in time) to apply (actually) to the Elect the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Benefit of that Freedom and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption purchaſed by himſelf.</p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:44024:33"/>
               <p> Thirdly, The deſign and office of the Holy Ghoſt, which is to ſanctify and renew the Souls of the Elect in effectual Calling, and to carry on and maintain the Work of Grace (begun in the Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver) to the end.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, The deſign of the Goſpel in revealing and diſcovering the Miſtery of Gods Love and Grace to his Elect and Choſen, which is, that Believers might (by virtue of Chriſts Death, ſavingly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed) Dye unto all Sin, and that they might (by virtue of Chriſts Reſurrection) walk in newneſs of Life before God.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, The deſign of Divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence towards true Believers, which is, to purge them from the remains of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dwelling Sin more and more, and to make them more and more to abound in Holy Conformity to Chriſt their Myſtical Head.</p>
               <p>All theſe (as ſo many Lines in a Center) do meet in the Doctrine of particular E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, the which when the Believer ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly conſiders, and (by Faith) applys to himſelf, he is ſo far from being drawn either to Sin or Deſparation thereby, as that he finds the quite contrary in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>viz.</hi> an admirable Averſion and Repugnancy, to yield conſent to the flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering Sollicitations of Sin, and an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:44024:33"/>hold, which powerfully keeps him from deſcending into the Darkſom Valley of Deſparation, which is (as I may ſay) the very entrance into Hell it ſelf.</p>
               <p>When the Believer is at any time at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacked by Satan, his enticing Inſtruments, or by indwelling Corruption, to yield to the motions of Sin, he fetcheth Arguments againſt Sin from the Doctrine of Gods Election thus: Hath God from all Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity fixt his gracious purpoſe of Deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Reſcuing me out of that ſtate of Sin and Miſery, into which the Apoſtacy of <hi>Adam,</hi> (my Natural and Faederal Head) plunged me, and that by chooſing out and fixing on his own Son to be a Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Saviour to purchaſe a liberty, and to work out a perfect and compleat Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption for me; and ſhall I? can I (with approbation) yield my full conſent to grieve and offend this freely and this dearly Loving God? I cannot do it, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can all the Craft and Pollicy of my Spiritual Enemies ever work me to a willingneſs to go back into that ſtate of Spiritual Captivity, under Sin and Satan, from which the Grace of God (in Election, and effectual Calling) hath ſet me free.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Hath Chriſt the Son of God, (purſuant to his Fathers Holy Decree and Gracious Purpoſe, and in compliance
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:44024:34"/>with ſo noble and glorious a Deſign, as Redeeming Captive Sinners, and recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciling them to his Father) conſented to become a Mediator for me, to work ou, a work of perfect Redemption for me that I might be ſet at liberty from the Laws Curſe, from the dominion of Sin, and the Uſurpation and Tyranny of the Devil? and ſhall I conſent to commit Sin againſt ſuch Bowels of Mercy and Love? I cannot do it.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Hath the Holy Ghoſt, (who in conjunction with the Father and the Son, had a Hand in my Election to Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life) vouchſafed to take on him the Office of a Sanctifier, to Sanctifie and Renew the Elect in effectual Calling, and who hath begun in me the Work of Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Sanctification, and will never (finally) leave me, till he hath perfected his Work begun in me; and ſhall I? can I willingly grieve and offend that Holy Spirit, by whom I am Sealed to the day of Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? I cannot do it.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Is the Goſpel appointed by Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt to be a Word of Revelation, to diſcover to me how the Heart of God, his Chriſt and Holy Spirit ſtood affected towards the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, (and toward me in particular) from Eternity and to endleſs Eternity; and not
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:44024:34"/>only ſo, but that the ſame might be a rule of Direction to me (all my Days) to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the falſe ways I am to ſhun and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void, as alſo the Paths I am to walk in, in order to a pleaſing the Holy Trinity, and coming ſafe to Heaven; and ſhall I? can I conſent to abuſe ſo ſweet and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent a Goſpel? I cannot do it.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, Is the deſign of Divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence (in all its various Diſpenſations to the Elect) and to me in particular, to purge Believers from the remains of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dwelling Corruption, and to make them more and more to abound in Holy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to Chriſt, their Myſtical Head; and ſhall I abuſe it by Sinning againſt it, and taking an occaſion therefrom to be vain and ſecure in my Converſation? I cannot do it.</p>
               <p>And as the true Believer is enabled, (being taught and guided by the Holy Ghoſt) to fetch Arguments againſt Sin from the five Sacred Topicks now men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned; ſo is he (in like manner) enabled, being ſavingly influenced by the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Holy Ghoſt in him, to fetch from the above Named Topicks, Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to keep him from final Deſparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in the moſt violent Hurrycane of Temptation which can attend on a deſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or an afflicted Condition.</p>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:44024:35"/>
               <p> To evince and clear up this Truth, (for the comfort and encouragement of the Pooreſt Believer, in an Hour of ſore Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs, when the Waters of Affliction reach even to the very Soul, to a ſenſible endangering the extinguiſhing the little Grace lodged in the Soul; let it be ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably and ſeriouſly conſidered, that the Believer when he finds Satan, his wicked Inſtruments, and indwelling Corruption all conjunctly together, preſſing and working his Soul within, to deſpair of Mercy and Salvation, he falls on Arguing from the ſweet Doctrine of Gods Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thus; ſhall I, can I who am ſecured of Life Eternal by the Gracious and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable Decree of the immutable God) deſpair of Mercy and Salvation, as Satan, the wicked World, and my own Carnal reaſon would have me do? I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not do it. If it were poſſible that my finking Soul ſhould drop (through the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Jaws of Deſpondency) into Hell it ſelf, from thence would Gods unchangeable purpoſe of Grace fetch and deliver it.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Shall I, or can I, for when Chriſt the Son of God hath undertaken (as a Sponſor and Surety) and for whom he hath wrought a perfect Reconciliation by his own Mediatorial Righteouſneſs, in which no Spot or Defect ever was, or
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:44024:35"/>ever ſhall be found by God, Angels or Men, deſpair of Mercy and Salvation, as Devil, wicked Men, and my own Carnal reaſon would fain perſwade me to do? I cannot do it.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, ſhall I, to and for whom the Holy Ghoſt is become a Sanctifier and a Renewer of my Nature, and who (by his ſaving influential Preſence) dwells in me, never (finally) to leave me till his good work of Grace begun in my Soul in effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual Calling, be compleatly perfected) deſpair of Mercy and Salvation, as the Devil, wicked Men, and my own Carnal reaſon would have me do? I can by no means do it.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Shall I who have all the ſweet and precious Promiſes of the Goſpel, of Gods Love and Grace to comfort and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure me, that God, Chriſt, and the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Spirit, will never, never fail or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake me, deſpair of Mercy and Salvation, as mine Enemies would perſwade me to do? I cannot do it.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, Shall I, (who have the Divine Providence engaged for me, to uphold me to purge out the remains of indwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Sin in me, and to forward me in conforming to my Myſtical Head Chriſt, in Holineſs, deſpair of Mercy and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, as mine Enemies would have me? I
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:44024:36"/>not do it. This is the uſe which a true Believer makes of the Doctrine of Gods Election (before time) while Faith (in the Believer) is in its right Exerciſe; none will ſtumble at it, (ſo as Eternally to Periſh) but ſuch as are not (by that Act of Gods Electing Decree) given to Chriſt (before time) to be actually Redeemed in time.</p>
               <p>Secondly, The Doctrine of Free Will and General Redemption, is a Doctrine which encourageth to Sin, and which (neceſſarily) leads to Deſparation. I ſhall offer two things to conſideration, for evincing and clearing up this for Truth; the which I deſire the Reader to weigh and conſider without prejudice.</p>
               <p>Firſt, The uſe which all unregenerate Men make of the Doctrine of Free Will, which ſad experience teacheth, is this: I will turn to God by Repentance, I will Believe in an Attoning Saviour, I will fall on the work of Reformation, and thereby prevent my periſhing by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved Judgments of God; when I ſee my own time, and when I am thereto diſpoſed; who ſees not, (except one Spiritually Blind) how greatly this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine doth encourage to Sin: For (ſaith my Carnal reaſon, as often it hath while I was in a ſtate of Nature) if I do not
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:44024:36"/>return to God upon his Call and Invita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion this Day, this Month, this Year, I fully purpoſe and reſolve to do it the next; for God hath implanted in my Soul a Principle of Free Will, whereby I am enabled to anſwer his Call, by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting, Believing and Reforming, the which when I do, (though not at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent) God will have Mercy on me, and I ſhall be accepted, being ſecured by that General Redemption provided for all who ſo Repent, Believe and Reform. Woful and ſad experience convinceth me, that many, God provoking Follys and Vanitys of Youth (in my Heart and Life) have been indulged by this decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, curſed Doctrine: Oh! how often hath Carnal reaſon (within me) cryed out, when the common Notions of the Spirit of God hath toucht my Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, to call on me to convert and turn to God? I will Repent, I will Convert, I will turn to God to morrow, to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row: As <hi>Auguſtin</hi> confeſſeth of himſelf, he often put God off with his Free-will, <hi>Cras, Cras; To morrow, to morrow.</hi> Till at length he grew both aſham'd and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his graceleſs to morrow, crying out to the Almighty (in the very hour of his effectual Converſion) <hi>Quam Diu Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine Clamabo Cras, Cras? Quare Non
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:44024:37"/>Hodiè Domine,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>How long, O Lord, ſhall I cry to morrow, to morrow? Why, O Lord, ſhould I not be Converted this veryday?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as an Unregenerate Man takes Encouragement from this Principle, to go on in Sin, ſo it leads him to Deſpara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Of this alſo my ſad Experience hath fully convinc'd me, as plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by the near approach I made to Hell, (in my own Apprehenſions) while I bordered ſo near the Confines of final Deſparation, finding in my ſelf how vaſtly ſhort my Perſonal Qualifications came of anſwering the Laws demand, as a Condition of Life and Salvation. I found that nothing could poſſibly quiet or ſatisfy my wounded, deſpairing Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, but what doth effectually ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſe and ſatisfy that Holy God, againſt whom I have ſo many thouſands of times offended, which can be nothing ſhort of an infinite Righteouſneſs; which Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs can be had no where but in Chriſt God Man, and no way to be had but in a way of Believing, of which My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery my blind and perverted Reaſon was as ignorant as a Beaſt: And not only ſo, but my Heart and Soul were Zealouſly ſet againſt looking for Life and Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in any other way than that of Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will and general Redemption.</p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:44024:37"/>
               <p> This Principle ſo every way Quadra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with my Legal Frame of Heart, which was acted by no other Principle: But do and Live.</p>
               <p>Here it might not be amiſs or unſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable (for the relief and encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a poor tempted Soul, who (as touching this very point of Election) may be walking in Darkneſs, having no light of Comfort in his own Spirit) to anſwer (or reſolve) this needful Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. How ſhall a poor, bewildred, temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Soul come to know, that it ſelf (in particular) was elected of God before time?</p>
               <p>To this Queſtion (about which many of God's called ones are not a little di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed in their own Spirits) I ſhall an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer in three Particulars.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> The way to know thou art ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted before time, is to go about it in a right way or manner. By this I mean, thou art not to attempt to pry into the Secret Counſels of the moſt High, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this Matter, knowing that ſecret things belong to God, and to none elſe, until he pleaſeth to reveal them, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.29. Therefore in order to know this Myſtery (to thy comfort,) do as thou wouldſt do, if thou wert to bring both
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:44024:38"/>ends of a Bottom of Thread or Yarn to meet together, the way is not to begin at that end which is hid in the very cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre of the Bottom, but to take the end which is outmoſt and next to thee; and by thus doing thou wilt ſoon bring both ends to meet, whereas if thou go about it in any other way, (as by cutting or ravelling the Bottom (to haſten the work) thou wilt but fret and vex thy ſelf, and (which is worſe) thou wilt marr and ſpoil the work. Do not then attempt (as the Devil and Carnal Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon would have thee) to climb up to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, to inform thy ſelf of this Matter; God's Work muſt be done in the way of his own Appointment; which is, that thou begin firſt with thy own Heart. See, examine and ſearch thy own Soul, to find out whether his Holy Spirit hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver been at work there? The Cauſe muſt be known by its proper Effects, not the Effects by the Cauſe. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.4. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10.</p>
               <p>Election (the thing thou wouldſt fain be reſolv'd about) is the cauſe (this is a Secret in God's Breaſt, which can be known by thee, no other way (ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily) but by its Effects, which are Faith in thy Heart, and Obedience to Chriſt's Commands in thy Life and Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:44024:38"/>If the Spirit of God hath called thee to embrace and cloſe with Chriſt, held forth in the Goſpel; and if the Fruits of that thy cloſing with Chriſt, do diſcover themſelves in thy Life and Converſation, thou haſt no Ground or Reaſon to queſtion thy Election, but what the Devil and thy Carnal Reaſon ſuggeſt. <hi>Acts</hi> 13.48. <hi>And as many as were ordained to eternal life, believed. Jo.</hi> 10.26. <hi>But ye believe not, becauſe ye are not of my ſheep, as I ſaid unto you.</hi> In the Scriptures now quoted, Election (to eternal Life) is held forth as the Cauſe of Faith and Faith (or believing in Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus) as the undoubted Fruit or Effect of Election.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Art thou frequently temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to doubt of, and queſtion thine Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to eternal Life?</p>
               <p>This is an undoubted Argument, that the Devil diſcerns in thee the Fruits and Effects of God's electing Love to thy Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, which puts him upon tempting thee to queſtion and doubt of God's Love to thee.</p>
               <p>Where the Devil knows he hath the full and quiet Poſſeſſion of a Sinner, there he ſuggeſts, that the Man is a good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian: His Faith is a good Faith, and
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:44024:39"/>God is his Father, and that he is elected and ſhall be Saved, notwithſtanding he lives after the Fleſh.</p>
               <p>On the contrary, where the Devil ſees and diſcovers the Fruits and Effects of God's Grace and Love appear, there he peſters the Soul with Infernal Suggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Temptations, to put the Soul on miſ-believing, and queſtioning the Truth of God's Grace beſtowed on the Sinner. Thou art but a painted Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite, thou art none of God's Elect; it is in vain for thee to hope or expect to go to Heaven. Thus he dealt with the Believers Redeemer. <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.3, 6. <hi>If thou be the Son of God,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And if the Adverſary hath done this to the green Tree, what will he not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to do to the dry? <hi>Luke</hi> 23.31.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Doſt thou find thine Heart (fixedly) reſolved (come Life, come Death) to caſt thy Soul at the foot of Divine Soveraignty, in the way of Duty, ſhunning all known Sin, and preſſing after Holineſs, reſting entirely on the Grace and Merit of Chriſt, after Life and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation? Thou art to know, for thine everlaſting Comfort and Encouragement, that no Reprobate ever was, or ever ſhall be able to do this. Time will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:44024:39"/>that thou art one of God's Elect; go on in the ſtrength of thy God: Fear not.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of Reprobation.</head>
               <p>BY what hath been diſcourſed out of the Holy Scriptures, concerning the Act of God's Election of ſome to Life and Salvation by Jeſus Chriſt, to the praiſe of the Glory of his own Grace; it unavoidably (and by neceſſary conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence) follows, that the ſame Soveraign God hath Reprobated (or Rejected) the reſt, (not ſo elected) and that from all E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity, having decreed never to recover them by converting Grace, but hath fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly purpoſed for Sin to Damn them; and that for the Praiſe of the Glory of his own Juſtice. Nothing can be more plain than that, if God hath elected and choſen a certain number out of the whole corrupted Maſs or Lump of fallen Mankind, in whoſe Salvation he hath purpoſed to Glorify his Mercy and free Grace by Jeſus Chriſt, then hath he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:44024:40"/>or paſſed by the reſt, as will moſt evidently appear in all the parts of it.</p>
               <p>The Decree of Reprobation hath in it four parts, to each of which I will ſpeak as plainly and as briefly as I can.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> God hath refuſed or rejected ſome particular Perſons, on whom he purpoſed never to have Mercy; this is moſt evident from the Scriptures follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. <hi>Jo.</hi> 10.26. <hi>But ye believe not, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ye are not of my ſheep, as I ſaid unto you. Rom.</hi> 11.7. <hi>But the election hath ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained it, and the reſt were blinded. Rom.</hi> 9.18. <hi>Therefore hath he mercy on whom he will have mercy, and whom he will he har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deneth.</hi> In which Scriptures it is plain and conſpicuous to every one (ſavingly) enlightened, that there are two diſtinct (or differing) Parties intended or ſpoken of, ſome, whom Chriſt choſe to himſelf, known and diſtinguiſhed by the Term, Sheep, and others, whom Chriſt denys to be ſo: Theſe are thoſe intended in <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.32, 33. termed Goats, oppoſed to the Sheep of Chriſt. Some, whoſe Underſtandings were ſavingly enlighten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to know the glorions Myſteries of the Covenant of Grace, in order to Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and others not at all enlghtened, but left to abide in that ſpiritual Darkneſs
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:44024:40"/>and blindneſs of Mind, which they brought into the World with them. Some, whom God's powerful Grace mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified and ſoftened to ſaving Repentance, in order to Mercy; and others, whom God ſees fit to harden, that is, to leave them to that Sin of their own, which hardens them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> God hath from Eternity re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected or refuſed theſe.</p>
               <p>This is plain from the Scriptures fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, <hi>Jude</hi> 4. <hi>There are certain Men crept in unawares, who were before of old ordained to this Condemnation.</hi> Rev. 17.8. <hi>Whoſe Names were not Written in the Book of Life from the Foundation of the World.</hi> 1 Pet. 2.8. <hi>And a Stone of ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling, and a Rock of offence, even to them which ſtumble at the Word, being Diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diem, whereunto alſo they were appointed. From all which it is manifeſt, that God did, (as a juſt Judge) purpoſe and decree to give up the Reprobates to the obſtinacy of their own Mind, and their wilful Diſobedience againſt his Son Jeſus Chriſt; that ſo they might not only ripen themſelves for, but even pull down the Judgments of God upon themſelves.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, God hath Decreed to Damn theſe Perſons for Sin.</p>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:44024:41"/>
               <p> This is plain from the following Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.4. <hi>The Lord hath made all things for himſelf, yea, even the Wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for the day of Evil.</hi> 2 Pet. 2.12. <hi>But theſe as Natural brute Beaſts, made to be taken and Deſtroyed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, Gods Reprobating ſome Perſons from Eternity, and that in order to Damn them for Sin, is for the Praiſe of the Glory of his own Juſtice.</p>
               <p>This is ſo plain and obvious, that he who runs may Read it. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.22. <hi>What if God willing to ſhew his Wrath, and to make his power known endured with much long Suffering, the Veſſels of Wrath fitted to Deſtruction.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againſt this Doctrine of Election, and Reprobation of particular Perſons, the <hi>Quakers, Papiſts, Arminians, Free-Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers</hi> and others, who (in this point) are all one with them, object ſeveral things, out of which I will ſingle out the chief and moſt material of their Objections, which to Ignorant and Injudicious Minds, ſeem to be of great force againſt the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines now laid down; to which I ſhall give plain and clear Anſwers from Gods Word, to the end the Fallaciouſneſs and Deceit of theſe Men might appear (open fac'd) to all Men.</p>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:44024:41"/>
               <p> Object. 1. <hi>They object, that to hold and affirm, that God hath from Eternity Elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and Choſen a particular number to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf out of the corrupted Maſs of fallen Mankind, on whom he decreed (unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably) to ſhew Mercy, leaving the reſt with a full purpoſe never to recover them to Life and Salvation, reflects on God the higheſt Cruelty imaginable.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> To this (ſeeming) plauſible Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, I ſhall reply in the particulars following.</p>
               <p>Firſt, I have made it evident from Gods own Word, that God hath (undenia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly) Elected a certain particular number to himſelf out of the corrupted Maſs of fallen Mankind, on whom he (unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably) decreed to ſhew Mercy, leaving the reſt (not ſo Elected) in that ſtate of Sin and Miſery, into which they (voluntari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) run themſelves.</p>
               <p>Secondly, By way of Query; I deſire to know by what Scripture (Divine) the <hi>Quakers,</hi> or any who are their Abettors in this point, can juſtify their bringing in Lyes to plead for God; or wherein doth it appear that his Truth ſtands in need of being upheld by the Figments of their vertiginous Brains.</p>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:44024:42"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Job</hi> puts ſuch a like Queſtion to his three Friends, who all ſeemed to take part with God againſt himſelf. <hi>Job</hi> 13.7. <hi>Will you ſpeak wickedly for God, and talk deceitfully for him?</hi> Verſ. 8. <hi>Will ye accept his Perſon? Will ye contend for God?</hi> Verſ. 9. <hi>Is it good that he ſhould ſearch you out? Or as one Man mocketh another, do ye ſo mock him?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What do theſe (Heretical Pretenders to an infallible Spirit) leſs than mock God? who (in pretence of making God more Merciful and Pitiful, than he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf hath revealed in his Word he will be, or than the Wicked in Hell will find him to be) ſtrike at, and (audaciouſly) diſpute againſt the Juſtice and Soveraignty of God.</p>
               <p>Theſe Pleaders for. God, they will (forſooth) have God to be ſo tender, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate and kind, as to love all his Creatures with an equal Love; and (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently) that to ſix his Love on a ſmall and particular number, to whom his Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Grace and Favour ſhould be extended, and to paſs by the greateſt number, on whom to reſolve never to ſhew Mercy; is altogether inconſiſtent with the tender, kind and merciful Nature of God. Now, whether theſe Men do not, (in pretence of Pleading for God) cauſe (as much as
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:44024:42"/>in them lyes) both his Attributes, his Counſels, and his Word, to claſh and contradict each other, I leave to the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious and unprejudic'd Reader to judge.</p>
               <p>I demand from <hi>John Burnyeats,</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> (who joyned with him in challenging me to make out by the Scriptures of Truth, that Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which I am now defending againſt them) why or wherefore God was ſo ſtrict and ſevere, as to confine thoſe Angels, which (of their own accord) fell from that ſtate of Innocency and Bleſſedneſs, wherein they were Created to thoſe Chains of Darkneſs, wherein they are to be kept to the judgment of the great day? and that without extending the Benefit of a Redeemer to them; was it becauſe the Angels were not his Creatures? certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they will not ſay ſo; for without Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute the Angels were in their Nature far more Glorious and Excellent Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, than was <hi>Adam</hi> and his Poſterity in their State of Innocency.</p>
               <p>Was it becauſe Gods Arm could not reach to help and deliver them? they dare not ſay ſo; neither was it becauſe God had no Bowels of Mercy and Compaſſion in him towards his Creatures: This can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſuppoſed to be the reaſon; for (alaſs) this, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the tender and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:44024:43"/>Nature of God to his Creatures (in general) is the Argument whereby they would overthrow the Doctrine of parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Election. What is the reaſon then? did the Angels fall by Sin and Apoſtacy? Yes, they cannot deny it, unleſs they deny the Scriptures to be the Scriptures of Truth; and were thoſe Angels (all of them) ſent forthwith to Hell for their Apoſtacy and Rebellion? this they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deny. Was not the leaſt Dram of Mercy ſhewn to one of that numberleſs number which fell? they dare not affirm there was, or ever ſhall be; if they do, it lyes at their Door to prove it.</p>
               <p>If then the reaſon why the Apoſtate Angels are (eternally) loſt, is not becauſe they ſtood not related to God as Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, nor becauſe the Hand of God was not ſtrong enough to prevent their ſink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into Hell; nor yet becauſe God want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Bowels of Mercy and Compaſſion: The reaſon then muſt be, becauſe the Glorious God did (before time) decree and purpoſe with himſelf, not to recover thoſe Creatures whom he foreknew would cauſeleſly Rebel and Apoſtatize from that ſtate of Holineſs and Happineſs, in which he decreed to make them.</p>
               <p>If then the Adverſaries I now contend with, will acknowledge God to be Juſt
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:44024:43"/>and Righteous in leaving the Angels, (which by Tranſgreſſion fell) ſo as never to ſhew them Favour more, I deſire to be informed by what Law the Soveraign Majeſty of Heaven can be (juſtly) charged with Cruelty, for Saving but a ſmall Remnant of Apoſtate <hi>Adams</hi> Offſpring, ſeeing that <hi>Adam</hi> was (every way) as vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary and free in Sinning againſt God, as were the Angels which fell.</p>
               <p>Surely, had it pleaſed God, he might have caſt both <hi>Adam</hi> and his Children into the ſame Lodging with <hi>Beelzebub,</hi> and his Apoſtate Train, there to endure (to endleſs Eternity) the Torments due to their Rebellion and Diſobedience.</p>
               <p>And in that God hath been pleaſed to extend Mercy to any of <hi>Adams</hi> Poſterity, it is meer Grace and Mercy (every way) undeſerved, the which he was no way bound to ſhew to <hi>Adam</hi> and his Children, any more than he was obliged or bound to help or commiſerate the fallen Angels.</p>
               <p>If <hi>John Burnyeat,</hi> or any of his Friends, (who oppoſe the Doctrine of particular Election) can prove (by the Scriptures) that God hath given (or is (by any Law) bound to give) Special Saving Grace to Rebels, who have fallen by their (cauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly) abufing and looſing the Grace given them in <hi>Adam,</hi> their Natural and Faede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:44024:44"/>Head; any other than what he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtows on his Elect, and that in the right of Election, I will readily ſubmit and yield the Cauſe.</p>
               <p>Object. 2. <hi>The Scriptures of Truth are expreſs and poſitive in affirming, that the Salvation diſcovered and held forth in the Goſpel, is deſigned by God, (and offered by the Apoſtle) to all Men (in general) without any diſtinction or limitation of Perſons; and therefore, to reſtrain that Salvation to a ſtinted number, is moſt injurious and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Theſe Cavilling Objectors do at a very eaſie rate wreſt and pervert the ſenſe of the Holy Spirit, not knowing what they ſay, nor whereof they ſo raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affirm, where they meet with univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Terms, from them they infer univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Principles, witneſs the Scriptures fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14.1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.6. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.9. Where the Apoſtle ſaith that Chriſt Died for all; and that he gave himſelf a Ranſom for all Men; and that he taſted Death for every Man: They from hence infer and ſtrongly conclude, (as they think) that beyond all Peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the end and deſign of Gods ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:44024:44"/>his Son into the World, and the Sons laying down his Life, was on full purpoſe that general Redemption might be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured for, and granted to all and ſingular the Sons and Daughters of lapſed <hi>Adam;</hi> and where the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> ſhews that God is not willing that any ſhould periſh, but that all ſhould come to Repentance. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.9. They would fain perſwade themſelves and all others, that without any reſtriction or limitation, the Senſe muſt be, that God wills not that any Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſhould be Damned.</p>
               <p>And ſo (fooliſhly) fond are they of the General Redemption, which (from the fore Cited Scriptures) they highly conceit themſelves able to demonſtrate and prove againſt all Gain-Sayers, that they (with great care) ſet down the Terms All, Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Any in great Capital Letters, that the Reader might obſerve and take notice of them.</p>
               <p>That thoſe Univerſal Terms All, Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Any, are to be reſtrained and limit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to a particular and ſelect number only, (which can be no other than that number which the Scriptures poſitively affirm, God Elected and Choſe to himſelf out of the corrupted Maſs; as hath been above obſerved) is beyond contradiction.</p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:44024:45"/>
               <p> The Objection conſiſts of two Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers (or Branches) Firſt, the deſign of God in preparing and intending Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Salvation for all Men in General. Secondly, Gods commanding to Preach (or offer) it to all in general, without exception: On theſe two miſtaken grounds the <hi>Quakers</hi> and the other <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks,</hi> who in this point join with them againſt the Word and Churches of Chriſt, do ignorantly and falſely infer that the Benefit of the ſecond <hi>Adams</hi> Obedience and Righteouſneſs, is (in Gods imputing and applying it) as extenſive, as was the Diſobedience and Rebellion of the firſt, which (ſay they) was to all the Poſterity of <hi>Adam.</hi> The places of Scripture from which they draw this their Unſcriptural Inference, are thoſe of <hi>Paul. Rom.</hi> 5.18. <hi>Therefore as by the offence of one, Judgment came upon all Men to Condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; even ſo by the Righteouſneſs of one, the Free Gift came upon all Men unto Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of Life.</hi> Heb. 2.9. <hi>But we ſee Jeſus, who was made a little lower than the Angels, for the ſuffering of Death, Crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Glory and Honour, that he by the Grace of God ſhould taſte Death for every Man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ground of theſe Mens looſing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in this Controverſie, is their uſing
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:44024:45"/>Scripture without Reaſon, and Reaſon without Scripture; the which whoever doth, will be ſure to run himſelf and his followers into a Labyrinth of dark and uncertain Interpretations of the moſt plain Text of Scripture, whence comes (moſt commonly) Chymerical and Enthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Notions, which are attended (as really) with a Satanical Energie, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Earthly Minded People, as the true Word of God is attended with a Divine Energie and Power, to teach and guide Gods Elect to the ſaving knowledge of God in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Here they ſeem (to the ignorant and unwary Reader) to have Scripture on their ſide, when oppoſing thoſe who aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert and defend the Doctrine of pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Election againſt theſe Univer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>(viz.)</hi> thoſe Scriptures above <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>; in which God ſeems to have intended the Redemption purchaſed by his Son, for every individual Son and Daughter of <hi>Adam;</hi> and that becauſe the Term ſet down is Univerſal.</p>
               <p>But now, theſe Men inhering in the bare Letter of the Scriptures, and laying aſide the uſe of Reaſon, (the which they ſhould make uſe of in diſtinguiſhing Terms) they themſelves, and their poor deluded Proſelytes looſe the true Senſe of
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:44024:46"/>the Scriptures, never looking farther than the bare Letter, never regarding whether they take the Senſe of the Spirit with them, yea or not.</p>
               <p>And hence it is, that with ſuch unbri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled Licentiouſneſs ſome Men do with higheſt confidence poſitively affirm, that the Salvation of the Goſpel is purchaſed and intended for all, and ſingular the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity of the firſt <hi>Adam;</hi> and that an univerſal offer thereof is (accordingly) made to each Man and Woman: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as (indeed) when the judicious and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prejudiced Reader joins Scripture and ſanctified reaſon together, accompanied with Self denial, and ſincere and hearty Prayer to Gods Throne of Grace, for the obtaining from God the true ſenſe of the Scriptures ſo much boaſted of, he will plainly ſee how egregiouſly they are miſtaken in both the one and the other; for neither doth God intend the Death of his Son for Salvation to any of <hi>Adams</hi> Children, ſave thoſe whom he Elected, and (from Eternity) Choſe in Chriſt; neither doth God make ſuch an Univerſal tender of it to all Men, as the <hi>Quakers</hi> raſhly and boldly affirm he doth.</p>
               <p>This lyes on me to demonſtrate and make good againſt theſe boaſting Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaliſts; the which, that I might do
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:44024:46"/>to ſatisfaction of the judicious and unpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiced Reader, I ſhall propound my Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument dilemma-wiſe, thus: The Terms All, Any and Every, on which they ground their Unſcriptural Aſſertion, they are to be taken either in an Univerſal ſenſe, intending every individual of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; or elſe they are to be taken in a limited and reſtrained ſenſe, as intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome of all ſorts, ranks and degrees of Men indifferently.</p>
               <p>If by the Univerſal Terms above na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, ſome of all ſorts, ranks and degrees of Men indifferently, be to be underſtood, then the Aſſertion of the Adverſaries is (manifeſtly) falſe, and conſequently the Doctrine of particular Election is true.</p>
               <p>If by thoſe Univerſal Terms all Men and Women without exception be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, (as the Adverſaries will have it) then muſt I be allowed to demand of them how any of <hi>Adams</hi> Children come to be Damned?</p>
               <p>For ſeeing that God willed that Chriſt ſhould Redeem all the Children of <hi>Adam,</hi> who fell by his Tranſgreſſion; I would fain know how any created Power can ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect the hindering God of bringing about his own purpoſe, or fruſtrate the end and deſign of Chriſt, in laying down his Life; for (undoubtedly) if God ſhould abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:44024:47"/>will and purpoſe the Salvation of every individual Son and Daughter of <hi>Adam,</hi> it is not to be queſtioned, but that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Elſhaddai,</hi> the Mighty God, every way perfect and all ſufficient, would find out ways and means to effect and bring about his own purpoſe, ſeeing that he works all things according to the Counſel of his own moſt Holy Will: As <hi>Paul</hi> witneſſeth, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.11.</p>
               <p>It is in the Work of Regeneration, as it is in the Work of the firſt Creation, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Cloaths his Word with a creating Power; ſo that whenever, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he ſends forth that creating Voice of his Mighty Spirit, neither Devil nor Self, nor any other Enemy or Impediment, whether internal or external, ſhall ever be able to give any ſtop to his intended Work: As the Lord himſelf tells his Church, by the Prophet <hi>Eſa.</hi> 43.13. <hi>Yea, before the day was, I am he; and there is none that can deliver out of my Hand: I will work, and who ſhall let it?</hi> Whom God in Juſtice and Righteouſneſs will Damn and Sentence to the Flames of his deſerved Wrath for Sin, who can reſcue and ſave them? Whom God in Sovereign Mercy and Grace purpoſeth to ſave and deliver, who can hinder or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent him? <hi>Jo.</hi> 10.27. <hi>My Sheep (ſaith
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:44024:47"/>the Lord Jeſus) hear my Voice, and I know them, and they follow me. And I give unto them Eternal Life, and they ſhall never pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, neither ſhall any Man pluck them out of my Hand. My Father which gave them me, is ſtronger than all; and no Man is able to pluck them out of my Fathers Hand. I and my Father are one.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here 'tis plain, that from the invinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Power of God and Chriſt, the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of the Life, and Salvation of the Elect, is inferred and proved.</p>
               <p>That many of <hi>Adams</hi> Children are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready in Hell, and that many more will be Lodged there; the Scriptures affirm, and the <hi>Quakers</hi> cannot deny. How comes this to paſs? ſeeing God (if we muſt Believe the <hi>Quakers</hi>) deſigned a general Redemption for all Mankind, and that the Son of God laid down his Life to Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom them from the Curſe and Wrath of God, due for their Sin, to ſay that God willed their Salvation, but that their own Obſtinacy and Wickedneſs hindred that his Will ſhould be accompliſhed on them; is (in effect) to ſay that God did ſeriouſly and efficaciouſly will and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that all the Children of <hi>Adam</hi> ſhould be ſaved; but indeed the grant eſt part of <hi>Adams</hi> Poſterity fell by the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:44024:48"/>of <hi>Satan,</hi> and their own rebellious Will.</p>
               <p>Now, whether to think or ſay, that either the power of the Serpent, or the corruption in a Sinners Nature, can, or ever did, or ſhall overturn or prevent the efficacious Will of God, being accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed, be not Impious and Blaſphemous; I leave to every impartial and ſober Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to judge.</p>
               <p>Thus the firſt Member (or Branch) of the Objection appears to be rotten and unſound; neither is the ſecond any bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which affirms that God makes a general offer of that Salvation to every individual Sinner in the World; the which if it be true, (as the <hi>Quakers</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm) they are highly obliged to ſhew how it comes to paſs that the greateſt part of the World (by far) ſhould remain in Darkneſs, I mean with reſpect to the very external means of Salvation; the which God hath ſeen ſit to deny to many Nations in the World; to which alſo the very Letter of the Holy Scripture bears witneſs. A few Inſtances hereof I lay down, that the Reader may plainly ſee, how vain theſe fooliſh Beaſters are in their Imaginations, who would fain im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe on all, that God doth love all the Children of <hi>Adam</hi> with an equal Love;
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:44024:48"/>and that the offer of his Grace (in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral) is made to all, without any excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or limitation; wherein they prove themſelves as falſe in their ſayings, as they appear vain in their deluded Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations.</p>
               <p>They ſay, and boldly affirm, that the tender of Salvation is made to all alike; I ſay, they belye the Spirit of God, (in pretence of pleading for God) by whoſe Inſtinct and immediate Inſpiration, they would make the World believe, they themſelves (above all Men) are guided; and not only ſo, but they egregiouſly thwart and contradict the very Letter of the Scripture, which they ſeem to own and acknowledge to be Holy, True, and the Rule and Standard of Tryal, of all matters in Religion wherein they and Chriſtians differ.</p>
               <p>For ſatisfaction herein, let the Reader peruſe, and with ſerious conſideration weigh in the ballance of Gods Sanctuary what is recorded in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147, 19.20. <hi>He ſheweth his Word unto</hi> Jacob, <hi>his Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes and his Judgments unto</hi> Iſrael. <hi>He hath not dealt ſo with any Nation: And as for his Judgments, they have not known them. Praiſe ye the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whether the place (now quoted, doth not evidently prove that when God choſe
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:44024:49"/>called and ſettled a Church unto his own peculiar Uſe and Service, to whom he gave his Word and Ordinances for a rule of Faith and Holy Obedience) he did not leave the other Nations of the Earth; (out of whom he choſe his People, with a peculiar Love and Favour) in their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Darkneſs and Blindneſs; is a matter to be enquired into. That of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our in <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.16. <hi>Many are called, but few choſen.</hi> Doth alſo give countenance to the point in hand: He doth not ſay that all are called, but many: In which Text there are three ſorts of Men offered to conſideration. Firſt, ſome who are not called at all. Secondly, ſome who are called with a common or external Call, but not Elected. And thirdly, ſome who are called, not only with the common and external Call, but alſo with the internal efficacious Call of the Spirit; and that becauſe Elected and Choſen to Life and Salvation. Now, that theſe three ſorts of People were equally Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of God, and their Salvation equally intended; who but Children of Darkneſs and Deceit dare to affirm or believe? That of <hi>Paul</hi> (alſo) <hi>Acts</hi> 14.16. <hi>God who in times paſt ſuffered the</hi> Gentiles <hi>to walk in their own way,</hi> Backs and confirms the preſent Truth: And doth not the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:44024:49"/>Account we have by Travellers, who correſpond with the moſt parts of the World, inform us, that the greateſt part of the Nations have not ſo much as the Name of Jeſus Chriſt among them; and even in theſe Kingdoms, where <hi>Popery, Arminianiſm</hi> and <hi>Quakeriſm</hi> prevail: Doth not ſad experience teach us how deplorable a Condition the generality of the Kingdoms is in? as touching the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Knowledge of Jeſus Chriſt, or the proper means appointed by God, for the ſaving Diſcovery of his juſtifying Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs to the Souls of Men; ſuch as the pure and unmixed Word of Truth, Read and powerfully Preached to them, for calling them out of Darkneſs into the marvellous Light of the Knowledge of God in Chriſt: For want of an Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox Teaching Miniſtry, theſe Kingdoms, (eſpecially <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi>) are near to a Harveſt ripeneſs, ready for the Sic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle of Gods Judgments, through the affected Ignorance of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, which reigns in the Minds and Hearts of the greateſt part, even of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> and <hi>Irelands</hi> Profeſſors; with the Occult and Spiritual Idolatry of Mens Souls, whereby the Son of God and his pure Goſpal Worſhip are ſhut out of Mens Hearts and Affections, that the Statutes
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:44024:50"/>of <hi>Omri,</hi> and their Carnal ſecular Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts might bear the ſway. To which I will add, that Deluge of open Debauch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ery, and Atheiſtical Oppreſſion and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneſs, which like a Land Flood over runs the Nations; the which, (if not very ſpeedily prevented by thoſe who have the Reforming Power put into their Hands by God) will pull down (from Heaven) ſuch ſore and deſolating Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as will make <hi>England</hi> with her Hypocritical formal Profeſſors an abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to all Nations. More might be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to conſideration from Gods Word to the ſame purpoſe; as the ſad and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable Condition the <hi>Epheſians, Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lippians,</hi> and other Countries were in, before the Apoſtles were ſent among them.</p>
               <p>The Anceſtors and Forefathers of whom, God ſuffered to Live and Die like Bruits, and worſe ſerving Dumb Idols, thoſe Teachers of Lyes, ſerving divers Luſts, Atheiſts, without the knowledge or hope of God in the World, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.1, 2, 3. To them God ſent no Prophet or Apoſtle, no Law or Goſpel, which ſhould be a means of Salvation to them, till God ſent <hi>Paul</hi> to their Off-ſpring.</p>
               <p>Now, can it (in truth) be ſaid, that God did equally love and will, or deſign
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:44024:50"/>the Salvation of both the Fathers and their Poſtery, ſeeing the means of Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation were deny'd to the Fathers, and freely given to their Poſterity?</p>
               <p>As touching the Learned (or rather Silly and Impertinent) Queſtion, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the <hi>Quakers</hi> deſire to be reſolv'd, <hi>(viz.)</hi> What Goſpel of glad Tidings it is which I (and others, who hold the Doctrine of Particular Election) have to Preach to thoſe, for whom Chriſt Died not?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This ſilly Queſtion is ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on a falſe Suppoſition, that Faith is required of all Men; the which I never taught, neither do I (now) own to be true.</p>
               <p>For, I do not think or believe, that ſuch as never heard of Chriſt, or who never had the means of knowing him, are required to believe, that Chriſt Died to Redeem them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> They are groſsly (if not wilfully) miſtaken, in thinking and ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that I preſs on all I Preach to, that it is their Duty to believe, that Jeſus Chriſt Died for them all, without any Limitation or Reſtriction. I do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that thoſe People, to whom the glad Tidings of the Goſpel is Preached,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:44024:51"/>are any of them required abſolutely, (and without Reſtriction) to believe, that Chriſt Died to Redeem them. All who ever attended on my Miniſtry, and who are able to give a Judgement, they will witneſs for me, that the ſcope and drift of my Preaching, is to convince and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waken Sinners out of their natural State, by opening up to them, from God's Word, the happy ſinleſs State, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in God Created them in <hi>Adam,</hi> their natural and faederal Repreſentative, how they came to fall from that Happy State, and what the ſad and wretched Effects of that Fall was to <hi>Adam,</hi> the Head, and now is to all his Children in their unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed State: This I do (inſtrumentally) by opening up to Sinners, the Senſe and Deſign of the Moral Law, which is to diſcover Sin, and to Damn the Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſors of it before God, to let Sinners know how ſpotleſs that Obedience and Righteouſneſs muſt be, which anſwers its own Demand, in order to its juſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them at the Bar of a Holy God. As alſo how weak and unable it is, to help a Lapſed Tranſgreſſor. It points out and requires Duty, but can afford no Ability or Strength to do that Duty: And all this, in order to bring Dead Sinners to a ſight and ſenſe of their need of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer.
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:44024:51"/>I labour to make them ſenſible, that out of Chriſt, no Life or Salvation is ever to be expected; and that until Chriſt the Son of God be received by a true Faith, they themſelves, with all their threadbare polluted Morality, and all thoſe Advantages, wherein they bleſs and count themſelves Happy, are all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Curſe of God, and Living and Dying ſo; they muſt (as certainly as God is Juſt, and his Law Holy) look to be eternally ſeparated from God and Chriſt for ever and ever. No Civility, goodneſs of natural Temper, no Mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, no Zeal for that which they take to be the beſt Religion, no learning or ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Parts, whether natural or acquired, no Riches or Greatneſs in this World will ever avail to keep them back from being (by the Laws powerful Sentence) ſent down to Hell.</p>
               <p>When I find and perceive, that the Spirit of God hath (by the Law ſet home on the Conſcience) brought the Sinner (with the Prodigal) to a ſenſe of his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done Condition, when I hear him cry out (not in a rotary and formal cuſtoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry way, which (God knows) is too much in uſe and faſhion in this ſleepy Hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Age) in the bitterneſs of his Soul, <hi>Mon and Brethren, what ſhall I do to be
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:44024:52"/>Saved?</hi> I then open up (as God's Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger) the Myſtery of God's Covenant of Grace held forth in the Goſpel, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is diſcovered the Incomprehenſible All-ſufficiency of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, to ſave and reconcile to God the greateſt and vileſt of Sinners. I preſently fall on directing and ſending the poor ſin-ſick wounded Sinner to the Son of God, with his Wounds and Plague-ſores, to be healed, preſſing him to believe in the Son of God, out of whom no Salvation is to be found. Hereto I add the peremptory Command of God himſelf, that the poor deſpairing Soul believe on the Son of God, 1 <hi>Jo.</hi> 2.23. <hi>Mark</hi> 16.16. By theſe Methods and Ways of God's own ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, God is pleaſed to work ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Converſion and effectual Faith in the Souls of elect Sinners.</p>
               <p>To what hath been offered out of God's own Word, to prove the Doctrine of Particular Election before time. I here ſet down the Judgment of the moſt Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Proteſtant Churches, concerning the ſame. Not that I think the Word of God ſtands in any need of Humane Teſtimony, to help it out, but rather to ſhew forth the ſweet Harmony which is between the Holy Scriptures and the Saints of God, (in their Holy and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:44024:52"/>Confeſſions of their Faith) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the preſent (ſo much controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and impugned) Doctrine of Election and Reprobation before time: As alſo to ſhame thoſe (nominal) Proteſtants, both Non. and Conformiſts, who have ſo apparently turn'd the back upon their own Articles of Faith, whereby both the one and the other Party hath (not a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle) ſtrengthened the Foundation of the Jeſuits hope of bringing <hi>England</hi>'s Neck (once more) under the Papal Yoke: From which I heartily wiſh, and ſincerely pray, that God will ever keep us.</p>
               <p>I begin with the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Predeſtination (to Life) is the everlaſting Purpoſe of God, whereby (before the Foundations of the World were laid) he hath conſtantly decreed (by his Counſel ſecret to us) to deliver from Curſe and Damnation, thoſe whom he hath choſen in Chriſt out of Mankind, and to bring them (by Chriſt) to everlaſting Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as Veſſels made to Honour. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, they which be endued with ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent a Benefit of God, be called ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to God's Purpoſe, by his Spirit, working in due ſeaſon: They (through Grace) obey the Calling; they be juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed freely; they be made Sons of God by Adoption; they be made like the Image
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:44024:53"/>of his only begotten Son Jeſus Chriſt; they walk religiouſly in good Works; and at length (by God's Mercy) they at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to everlaſting Felicity. See 39 Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle 17th of <hi>Predeſtination</hi> and <hi>Election.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Confeſſion of Faith, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed upon by the Aſſembly of Divines at <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By the Decree of God, for the Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of his Glory, ſome Men and Angels are predeſtinated to everlaſting Life, and others to everlaſting Death, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.21. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.41. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.22.</p>
               <p>Theſe Angels and Men thus Predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated and fore Ordained, are particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and unchangeably deſign'd, and their number is ſo certain and definite, that it cannot be either encreaſed or diminſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p>Thoſe of Mankind, that are Predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated unto Life, God, before the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the World was laid, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his eternal and immutable Purpoſe, and the ſecret Counſel and good Pleaſure of his Will, hath choſen in Chriſt unto everlaſting Glory, out of his meer free Grace and Love, without any foreſight of Faith, or good Works, or Perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in either of them, or any other
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:44024:53"/>thing in the Creature, as Conditions or Cauſes, moving him thereunto; and all to the praiſe of the Glory of his Grace.</p>
               <p>As God hath appointed the Elect unto Glory, ſo hath he, by the eternal and moſt free Purpoſe of his Will, fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordain'd all the means thereunto, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.4, 5. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.10. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.13. Wherefore, they who are Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, being fallen in <hi>Adam,</hi> are Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Chriſt, are effectually called unto Faith in Chriſt, by his Spirit working in due Seaſon, are Juſtified, Adopted, San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified, and kept by his Power, through Faith unto Salvation, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.9, 10. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.14. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.10. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.5. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5.</p>
               <p>Neither are any other Redeemed by Chriſt, effectually Called, Juſtified, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dopted, Sanctified, and Saved, but the Elect only. <hi>Jo.</hi> 17.9. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28. <hi>Jo.</hi> 10.26.</p>
               <p>The reſt (of Mankind) God was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, according to the unſearchable Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of his own Will, whereby he extend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth or withholdeth Mercy as he pleaſeth, for the Glory of his Soveraign Power (over his Creatures) to paſs by, and to ordain them to Diſhonour and Wrath for their Sin, to the praiſe of his glorious
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:44024:54"/>Juſtice, <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.25, 26. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.12. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.8.</p>
               <p>See <hi>The Aſſemblys Confeſſion of Faith,</hi> Chap. 3. of the eternal Decree of God.</p>
               <p>To this, the Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> hath fully agreed: With this alſo agrees the Articles (of Faith) of the Church of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> in Biſhop <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi>'s time. See thoſe Articles: And <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi>'s Body of Divinity. Queſt. <hi>What are the parts of Predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? Anſw.</hi> Election and Reprobati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.9. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.13, 22, 23.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What is Election? Anſw.</hi> It is the everlaſting Predeſtination or Fore-appointing of certain Angels and Men unto everlaſting Life and Bleſſedneſs, for the praiſe of his Grace and Goodneſs, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.21. <hi>Jo.</hi> 15.16. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.22, 23. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.4, 5, 6, 9.</p>
               <p>Queſt. <hi>What is Reprobation? Anſw.</hi> It is the eternal Predeſtination or Fore-appointment of certain Angels and Men unto everlaſting Diſhonour and Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, God (of his own freewill) deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining to paſs them by, refuſe or caſt them off; and (for Sin) to Condemn and Puniſh them with eternal Death. <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.4. <hi>Exod.</hi> 9.16. <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.17, 22. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.20. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.41. See <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi>'s <hi>Body of Divinity,</hi> pag. 91, 92.</p>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:44024:54"/>
               <p> The Church of <hi>France</hi> (in the 12th Article of the Confeſſion of her Faith) hath theſe words, <hi>(viz.) We believe that God, out of that Corruption and general Curſe, into which all Men were plung'd, doth free thoſe whom (in his eternal and immutable Counſel) he elected of his meer Goodneſs and Mercy in our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, without the Conſideration of Works, leaving the reſt in the ſame Corruption and Damnation, to ſhew forth in theſe his Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and in them the Riches of his Mercy, for none of them are better than others, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God hath ſeparated them,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The Synod of <hi>Dort</hi> in the 7th Canon doth lay down this plain and clear Defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition of Election, thus, <hi>(viz.) Election is the unchangeable Purpoſe of God,</hi> by which, before the Foundation of the World, (according to the free good pleaſure of his Will) of his meer Grace, he hath choſen out of all Mankind to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation in Chriſt, a certain and ſet num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Men, neither better nor more worthy than others; but lying in the common Miſery with others, and fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len from original Righteouſneſs, into Sin and Deſtruction, by their own fault, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And in the 15th Canon of Reprobati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they ſay thus, <hi>(viz.) The Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture doth manifeſt and commend unto us this
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:44024:55"/>eternal and free Grace;</hi> eſpecially when it doth farther witneſs, <hi>That not all Men are elected, but that ſome are not elected, or are paſſed by in the eternal Election of God,</hi> (viz.) Thoſe whom God (accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his free juſt, unreproveable and immutable good Pleaſure) decreed to leave in the common Miſery, into which they had caſt themſelves, by their own fault, and not to give to them ſaving Faith, and the Grace of Converſion.</p>
               <p>It were (almoſt) endleſs to inſert all the Confeſſions and the Judgments of the Orthodox, (in all Ages) who have held and (with an unſhaken Confidence) maintain'd to the Death, the very ſame Faith, concerning the Doctrine of Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Reprobation, on whom (with the Pen-men of Holy Writ) the frothy <hi>Arminians</hi> of the Age we live in; who are more Crafty, than truly Wiſe, do not ſpare to caſt the baſeſt Reflections, as if they were no way worthy to compare with themſelves, for either Learning, Parts, or Piety. But whatever others think, for my part, I am neither affraid nor aſham'd to tell them, that the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances they are daily making towards the Scorners Seet, in contemning and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dervaluing the bright ſhining ones gone to Glory; it is to me an invincible Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:44024:55"/>not only of their being deſtitute of true ſaving Grace; but that this their priding it over the beſt of Men, is a ſure Prognoſtick of their own Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, when the overflowing Scourge threatened in <hi>Eſa.</hi> 28.15. comes on <hi>England.</hi> The <hi>Arminian</hi> Drugs of Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will, (in fallen Man) general Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, falling from Grace, with temporary Conditional Election, reviv'd and ſown (in <hi>England</hi>) by the Jeſuits Art, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagated by too many Preachers of the two Parties above-mentioned, have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the moſt ſucceſsful Expedients, to lay <hi>England</hi> open to utter Ruine, that ever thoſe Incendiaries of the World could deviſe. And indeed the poiſonous Drugs (now mentioned) have ſo Epide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mically overſpread the Nation, that I cannot ſee how the Land can be cured (in an ordinary way) any other way, than by the Preachers of both Parties, (who have imbib'd thoſe poiſonous Principles, and (by Preaching) convey'd them (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſibly) into the Heads and Affections of of the People) Vomitting up (by ſound Repentance) thoſe curſed Principles, as ſome have done their Doctrine of Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Obedience and Non reſiſtance, the which had they not done, the Land (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this time) would (in all probability)
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:44024:56"/>have been turn'd into an <hi>Aceldama,</hi> or a Papal Slaughter-houſe. Vomitting up, I ſay, (by ſound Repentance) the curſed Principles above mentioned, and labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in Preaching up the Soul-ſaving Doctrine held forth in the 39 Articles of Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and the Aſſemblys Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Faith, (on which they have ſo ſhamefully and apoſtatically turn'd the back) to undeceive the People, who (by their means) have been ſo ſadly corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in their Principles, and (by reaſon of thoſe Principles) ſo wretchedly engulfed in the Quagmire of Debauchery and open Prophaneneſs.</p>
               <p>It will prove their own, and the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons great Advantage, to endeavour (ſeaſonably and Cordially) to Retrieve the ground they have loſt, by their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh Compliance with the corrupt and erring Humour of the two laſt Reigns; and that by ſounding (in their reſpective Pulpits) a timely Retreat, and exhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the People (with them) to a cordial Reception of their Abdicated Articles of Religion; from which the Infernal Craft of <hi>England</hi>'s Enemies, and their own ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine Incautelouſneſs have drawn them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide. It is (infinitely) better for ſuch manifeſt Corrupters of the true Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Doctrine, to own their Errors, and
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:44024:56"/>repent of them here, while the Gate of Mercy is open; and all true Proteſtants Hearts and Arms are open, ready to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them, on their return from the Communion of the worſt and moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious of the Churches and poor <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>'s Enemies, than to own and repent of their Errors and Prevarications in Hell; of which place ſuch Men cannot but know it is ſaid, <hi>Ab infernis nulla Redemptio:</hi> There is no Redemption or Returning from Hell. This the Inhabitants of that place know (Experimentally,) to their endleſs and remedileſs Sorrow and Grief. From which place, ſhould it pleaſe the Holy Soveraign of the World, to ſend the moſt Gigantick Diſputers, (againſt the Doctrine of God's free Election of particular Perſons before time) which are now Tongue-ty'd in that place of Torment, to <hi>London,</hi> to relate what they know (by ſad Experience) ſince Death arreſted them, they would be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced (I doubt not) to declare, that no Wit or Parts, (natural or acquired) no Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage or Magnanimity of Mind, no Mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity or perſonal Qualifications acquirable (by any of <hi>Adam</hi>'s Children) is, or can be Armour proof againſt the Vindicative Proceedings of an Angry and a Sin re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venging God againſt thoſe <hi>Papiſts, Armi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:44024:57"/>Socinians, Freewillers,</hi> &amp;c. now in Hell, who (when on Earth) did bend all their Wit and Learning to run down and ridicule the Doctrine I am now Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating. It will be well for their Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, (who are yet this ſide Hell) if this plain dealing with them prove an occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of awakening them, and putting them upon a ſerious Conſideration of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent State they are in, and the way they walk in, that being ſavingly convinced, both of the Wretchedneſs of the one, and the Deſtructiveneſs of the other, they may be driven (by a Holy Deſpair of ever being ſaved in an unregenerate State, and walking in ways of their own deviſing) to ſhelter themſelves under the ſhadow of that Mediatorial ſpotleſs Righteouſneſs of the Son of God, by a ſound Faith, and an Evangelical Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, which the Spirit and Word of the ever Bleſſed God aſſures me, is the only way to eſcape Hell and eternal Ruine, which is all the harm I dare to wiſh them, and the greateſt Enemies I have now Living.</p>
               <p>I conclude my Treatiſe with an <hi>Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getical Reply to,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="reply">
            <pb n="101" facs="tcp:44024:57"/>
            <head>An Apologetical Reply to the Slande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Charge given in againſt me, to ſome of the <hi>London</hi> Miniſters, by that Malecontent Party, which (Schiſmatically) ſeparated from the Church in C. whereof I was the (then) Lawful Paſtor.</head>
            <p>THE Charge was, That I was a Man of an Independant Judgment, a great Enemy to Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> declaring, that Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> is Damn'd in Hell, a Man who (openly) declar'd, that Chriſt hath but two or three true and faithful Miniſters, (in and about <hi>London</hi>) who Preach Chriſt in Truth, and who bid a publick Challenge to Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> (and all the <hi>Baxterians,</hi>) to diſpute certain Poſitions held and aſſerted by Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> and ſuch as go his way, and (to add no more) one who is an univerſal Decryer of all the Duties of Holineſs in a Chriſtians Life and Converſation, crying out, (in
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:44024:58"/>the Pulpit) <hi>Away with your Holineſs, to Hell with your Duties and perſonal Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Charge conſiſts of five branches or parts, to each of which I will ſpeak as diſtinctly as I can, and that with as great Seriouſneſs and regard to Conſcience, as if I were to make the preſent Defence at the Bar of the Great Judge.</p>
            <p>I begin with the firſt, <hi>(viz.)</hi> My be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an Independant, I have this to ſay for my ſelf, firſt, the Congregational way (of Church Government) is the Principle which (according to my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent light) I apprehend to be neareſt to the Platform of Goſpel-Churches, plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Apoſtles, which to own and practiſe, I am (fully) convinc'd, is my Duty: For which, I humbly hope and charitably believe, none of my Brethren of the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Perſwaſion dare to cenſure or blame me, until I can ſee, that I am herein miſtaken and out of the way.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> As touching my Judgment (herein) I do affirm, (and that in truth) God knows I lye not, I honeſtly and fairly acquainted my (now) Reproachers, what I was in my Judgment, (as to this very Point) when they firſt diſcovered an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:44024:58"/>to call me to take the Paſtoral Charge of their Souls: About this, they and I had ſeveral (occaſional) Diſcourſes <hi>Pro.</hi> and <hi>Con.</hi> for and againſt it; and in concluſion they (with the reſt of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanters with God, in a Church way) did own themſelves fully convinc'd, that the Congregational way (of Church Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment) was (moſt certainly) the way of the Goſpel; and as ſuch, they freely cloſed with me. If what I have now aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted be deny'd, I ſhall (by Authentique Teſtimonies) make the ſame good to their Faces.</p>
            <p>I come to the ſecond Branch of the Charge, <hi>(viz.)</hi> My being a great Enemy to Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In anſwer whereto, I poſſitively af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, that I never (in my Life) had any Prejudice againſt Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> ſave only to diſlike and caution my Flock againſt ſome Notions of his, wherein I concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him to be Heterodox in the Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Principle of Juſtification. I told my Auditory, as plainly as I could ſpeak, that in mentioning Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Name, my deſign was not to meddle in Judging him, as touching his Eternal State, only what of Corruption I found in his Books, I judg'd it my Duty to take notice there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:44024:59"/>and to caution my Hearers (who had his Books) to beware of ſuch Notions. And what I did herein, I did it (God and my Conſcience knows) in Faithfulneſs to Chriſt, and the Souls of thoſe commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to my Paſtoral Charge by the Great Shepherd of the Sheep.</p>
            <p>But to ſay, that Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> was Damn'd (in Hell,) I abhor the very hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or thoughts of ſuch a thing; neither dares any one living (except a cauteriz'd and brazen fac'd Sinner) to charge ſuch a Slander on me; ſo far was I from utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch an uncharitable (I may ſay Infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal) Expreſſion, that I plainly ſpoke the contrary, (as my Judgment of him) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring, that I hoped Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> was with Chriſt in Glory; and that I dare to think, no otherwiſe. As for what of Corruption, which is mixt with his Writings, I told my Auditory, I lookt on that as a part of the Wood, Hay and Stubble intended by the Apoſtle in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.12. of which Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> will (I doubt not) ſuffer the Loſs in the Great day, though he (himſelf) be ſaved, he hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſt the Foundation, firm and ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt to the end, as (in Charity) I hope he did.</p>
            <pb n="105" facs="tcp:44024:59"/>
            <p> The third Branch of the charge is, that I affirmed, that Chriſt had but two or three right Goſpel Miniſters, who Preach Chriſt (truly) in and about <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I anſwer in the Negative, <hi>viz.</hi> That I never thought or ſpoke ſuch a thing, either in or out of the Pulpit in all my Life.</p>
            <p>The occaſion of this Slander was this, I was (in a Sermon) bewailing the ſmall number of right Goſpel Preachers; at which time, and on which occaſion, I ſaid, that a great many Preach'd up the Pope: That <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that Man of Sin. Others (ſaid I) Preach up the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Hierarchy, and its Intereſt; inſtead of the Kingdom of Chriſt. Others there be (ſaid I) who Preach up <hi>Moſes,</hi> and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to his do, and live, in the room of Chriſts Mediatorial ſpotleſs Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, for Juſtification and Life; ſo that (in compariſon) it is (undeniably) true, that Chriſt hath but few who Preach him and his immaculate Righteouſneſs, as the only Meritorious and procuring cauſe of Juſtification and Salvation. This is what I ſaid (then) and truly I ſee but ſmall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to think or ſay otherwiſe: I queſtion not, but the Orthodox (in and about <hi>London</hi>) will readily Harmonize with me herein: But that I did limit the true Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:44024:60"/>of Chriſt to any certain (definite) number; or that I mentioned any Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters Names (by way of diſtinction) I ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly deny. And I have very good reaſon to judge it no breach of the Law of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, to believe that the ſecret deſign of the Reporters hereof, was to incenſe and provoke the Spirits of Godly Miniſters, and their reſpective Congregations againſt me. And (hereby) to prepare them for a more facil and ready reception of the other black and ſcandalous Reproaches, which were to be brought on the Stage, on purpoſe to do my buſineſs; as one of their Confederates was heard to ſay he would do. I come to the fourth Branch of the Charge, which is, That I ſhould bid a publick challenge to Mr. <hi>Williams,</hi> (and the reſt of Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi> followers) to Diſpute certain Poſitions held (and aſſerted) by Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> and thoſe who go his way.</p>
            <p>To which I reply, That this is as true as the reſt, and did (I am very ſure) proceed from the ſame lying Spirit which Coined and Forged their other lying Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries againſt me; the deſign whereof, was not only to corroborate that their Deſign (in its Foundation) but alſo to draw over Mr. <hi>Williams</hi> (and others, whom they knew to be impatient to hear any Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:44024:60"/>given to any Notions of Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi>) to them; to help and encourage them to break that Church, whereof themſelves were an Eſſential part, and to force my flight from my Station in C. to which their own Electing Voice called me.</p>
            <p>The occaſion of this Slander was thus, I did one day (in Preaching) lay down this Poſition, <hi>viz.</hi> That an Elect Sinner is (in effectual Calling) freely juſtified from all charge of Sin, both Original and Actual, by the alone Mediatorial Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, freely imputed by God; and that without any regard had to any Conditions performed by, or Qualifications inhering in the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Sinner, (as con Cauſes with Chriſt in Juſtification) This (ſaid I) is a truth ſo clearly laid down and aſſerted in the Goſpel, and ſo back'd with the wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Gods Spirit (in the Hearts of all aſſured Believers) that all the Diſputers in the World, (who oppoſe the ſame) will never be able to overthrow it, be their Wit and Parts never ſo ſharp and admired. And whether I be miſtaken (herein) I freely appeal to the Judgment and Determination of all Orthodox Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants; who (in the point of Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) are not more or leſs tainted with
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:44024:61"/>the <hi>Ropiſh, Arminian</hi> Leaven of Free Will and General Redemption.</p>
            <p>But to bid a challenge to Mr. <hi>Williams,</hi> (or any others) to diſpute matters of Controverſie in Religion; I do (moſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly) profeſs, I never ſpake ſuch a thing, either in or out of the Pulpit.</p>
            <p>The fifth and laſt Branch of the black Charge brought in againſt me, was, That I am an Univerſal Docryer of all Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Duties in the Life and Converſation of a Chriſtian: Crying out (in the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit) <hi>away with your Holineſs,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The deſign of my Accuſers (in this) was to repreſent and expoſe me as a rank <hi>Antinamian,</hi> and ſo I ſhould prove, were the Accuſation true.</p>
            <p>But to let all (who read this) ſee withwhat a virulent and malicious Spirit the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triver and Preſenter of this black Charge, (againſt me) was Acted; I (here) ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and conſcientiouſly ſet down the very Words I ſpake, from which, the occaſion was taken to repreſent me in ſuch black Colours. The thing was thus, the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject I was then upon, leading me to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the ſad and deplorable Condition the Poor Sinner is in (while in a ſtate of Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regeneracy) I had theſe Expreſſions, (whoſe deſign and tendency was to awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and convince the Sinner of his Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:44024:61"/>by Nature) by way of obſervation, <hi>viz.</hi> That where God ſets the Law on work in the Conſcience of an unconverted Sinner, it will (like the Avenger of Blood) purſue the Guilty Sinner, till it either drive the Sinner to Chriſt, (the only City of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge) or till the Sinner he Lodged in Hell.</p>
            <p>To bring the matter home more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly and cloſely, to an awakened Conſcience, labouring (with <hi>Adam</hi>) to cover the Sinner with the Fig-leaves of Self-rightcouſneſs, (both Negative and Poſſitive) thereby to be juſtified and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved: I addreſs'd my ſelf to this Sinner, in theſe words, <hi>Thou convinc'd (Rebel) Sinner! who art now under the Laws Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, and ſinking under the heavy weight of thy Sins, hoping to relieve and lick thy ſelf whole with thy Conditions and Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications, as if there by thou couldſt make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends to the offended Juſtice of God, for all thy Violations of his Righteous Law, know, and conſider it thou muſt, that the Juſt and Righteous Law of God. (whoſe terrible Sentence (in thy guilty Conſcience) thou art now ſtriving to fly and ſhun in this way of Works) it is like a ſtrict Creditor, who will not accept (for Payments) any Coin, which appears ſhort and deficients either in Quantity or Quality:</hi> It will not
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:44024:62"/>hear of a Sinner's being juſtified by any Works; but ſuch as are exactly Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurate to its own Juſt and Holy Demands. Now (ſaid I) either ſee that thy Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Qualifications (whereunto thou truſteſt for Life and Salvation) be ſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, and exactly commenſurate to the Law's Demand, or in caſe they be not, then away with thy Fig-leaf Holineſs, to Hell with thy Duties and perſonal Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications. Look to the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, (by an Eye of Faith) caſt thy weary ſinking Soul on him for Life and Salvation, or thou wilt Periſh eternally, <hi>Jo.</hi> 3.36. <hi>Jo.</hi> 8.24. This is what I ſaid (then,) Chriſt knows I Lye not, my Conſcience alſo bearing me witneſs in the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>When I have to do with believing Chriſtians, I preſs them to the Duties of practical Holineſs and good Works, as if they were to be juſtified and ſaved by them. But ſtill, with this ſeaſonable Caution, that Believers do never join their Works of Sanctification with Chriſt's juſtifying Righteouſneſs in the Work of Juſtification.</p>
            <p>Beſides the black Charge brought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, to which I have ſpoken by way of Apology, mine Accuſers (the better to palliate their own black and horrid.
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:44024:62"/>Crimes) charge me with Defectiveneſs in my Life and Converſation, as not practiſing what I Preach. To this I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply in four Particulars.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> By way of Conceſſion (or Grant) my Life and Converſation is not accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to my Preaching; in a ſenſe I own it, I do (humbly) acknowledge, (with ſhame and grief) that I find my ſelf vaſtly ſhort of that Perfection (in Sanctification) which (in Preaching) I preſs (as Duty) on my ſelf and others; and the Searcher of Hearts beſt knows of how great a Concern it is to me, to reflect on the vaſt Diſparity which I (ſenſibly) perceive is between what I am, and what I ought to be in point of Conformity to Chriſt, in Life and Converſation, which lays me under an indiſpenſible neceſſity of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing to that <hi>Video meliora proboque deteriora ſequor.</hi> I know and approve better things, but follow or encline to things which are worſe: And to that of <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 7.24. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>O wretched man that I am,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> By way of Negation, if my Accuſers intend and mean, that I give my ſelf up to a courſe of diſſolute and looſe Living, or that I allow my ſelf in
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:44024:63"/>the approved Practice of any Immorality, which is incompatible with a Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate State, or which is Inconſiſtent with a Holy Poſſeſſion; I abſolutely (through ſpecial Grace) deny the Charge, and do bid my Invidious Beſpatterers (and all ſuch as do (uncharitably) credit ſuch malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Reports of me) a fair and ſober Challenge, to make good ſuch a Charge againſt me, by any Authentick Witneſs, which is not known to be prejudic'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, (if not one or more of them) who have plotted to overthrow my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation and Miniſtry.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> If ſhort coming in living up to what I Preach and Profeſs, be a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Warrant for Church Members, to prevaricate and run away, (like Children of <hi>Belial</hi>) throwing off the Yoke of Duty, (in the Church;) I would gladly know how it is poſſible for any Churches to be kept up on Earth, conſidering that the Inſtruments, by whoſe Miniſtry God ſees fit to gather and Build up Churches, to fit them for Glory, are frail Men, not ſinleſs Spirits.</p>
            <p>For my own part, albeit I am far from pleading for any Sin, (though but the leaſt Infirmity) whereof either I my ſelf,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:44024:63"/>or any other know me Guilty. I muſt needs ſay, that I never yet could find, that ever God the Father (in the <hi>Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament,</hi>) or Chriſt his Son (in the <hi>New,</hi>) did call or ſend any to be Prophets or Apoſtles, who were exempt or free from perſonal Failings; or who were ever a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to live up (perfectly) to the Doctrine they Preached to others: Yea, it is moſt evident, (to any intelligent Reader) that a conſiderable part of the Canon of Holy Scripture is Occupant about diſcovering, acknowledging and bewailing the ſinful Miſcarriages and ſhort comings of the Pen-men thereof, as the Learned and Godly well know.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly, and Laſtly,</hi> Suppoſing that my Brethren knew and could prove me guilty of as great Falls as ever any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned Sinner fell into; is it not the duty of Church Members, to endeavour my Recovery, by coming to me in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Meekneſs, and Brotherly Love, to call on me, and to ſtir me up to Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and Reformation? knowing than the Holieſt of Saints, (even thoſe of the higheſt Attainments in Grace) while in the Body, are Obnoxious to the ſpreſt Temptations; and by reaſon thereof
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:44024:64"/>(and the remains of indwelling Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) are liable to the ſoreſt falls thereby.</p>
            <p>The Word of God proves, that ſo to do is the undoubted Duty of Church Members one towards another, <hi>Lev.</hi> 19.17. <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.15. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.1. But this my Schiſmatical Brethren never did to me, though never ſo earneſtly Courted, and lovingly Entreated thereto; and that both in and out of the Pulpit: As can be ſufficiently prov'd if need be.</p>
            <p>Satan and his plotting Agents knew (fullwell) that the old Trade, <hi>Report, and we will report it, Jer.</hi> 20.10. was the moſt likely and effectual way to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh their ungodly Deſign, which was to unchurch the Church, and (for future) to render my Miniſtry uſeleſs: In order whereto the Paſtor muſt firſt be attackt, according to <hi>Zach.</hi> 13.7. <hi>Smite the ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd, and the ſheep ſhall be ſcattered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Apology I thought not only Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient, but my Duty to publiſh, for the true Information of thoſe, (eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Diſſenting Miniſters) who have (from the Character given them of me, by thoſe I here intend) ſuckt in Prejudice againſt my Name and Miniſtry.</p>
            <pb n="115" facs="tcp:44024:64"/>
            <p> And to occaſion their (ſeriouſly) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering, how (every way) unbecoming the Goſpel it is, for one Chriſtian (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſuch as are called to Sacred Office) to be open Ear'd, and of too credulous a Temper, in liſtening to, and improving (to the great Prejudice of thoſe, whom the Law of Charity commands them to love) any Reports, which looks like a Deſign to blacken or ſtain the Reputation of a Brother, eſpecially a poor Stranger, who (for Chriſt and the Goſpel) hath loſt his All; and who (for witneſſing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſpreading Errors of the times) is ſurrounded and beſieged with Enemies of all ſorts. To frown on, and carry it ſtrange to ſuch, will neither pleaſe God, credit Religion, or help to make a dying Bed eaſy and comfortable, <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.21. <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.19. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.12. <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 3.12, 13, 14, 15.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obſequium Amicos, veritas Odium parit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Flattery begets Friends, ſpeaking Truth cauſeth Enemies. Compare <hi>Eſa.</hi> 30.10. with <hi>Amos</hi> 5.10.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
